<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Antinomians and familists condemned by the synod of elders in Nevv-England: with the proceedings of the magistrates against them, and their apology for the same. Together with a memorable example of Gods iudgments upon some of those persons so proceeded against.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 219 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96714</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3094</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E251_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212499</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871108</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871108</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159091</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96714)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159091)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 43:E251[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Antinomians and familists condemned by the synod of elders in Nevv-England: with the proceedings of the magistrates against them, and their apology for the same. Together with a memorable example of Gods iudgments upon some of those persons so proceeded against.</title>
                  <author>Winthrop, John, 1588-1649,</author>
                  <author>Weld, Thomas, 1590?-1662,</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ralph Smith at the signe of the Bible in Cornhill neare the Royall Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to John Winthrop and to Thomas Weld, who signed the preface of a later edition (Wing W3095A).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 16 1643"; final 4 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hutchinson, Anne Marbury, 1591-1643 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Antinomianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Massachusetts --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159091:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANTINOMIANS AND FAMILISTS CONDEMNED By the SYNOD of ELDERS IN NEVV ENGLAND: WITH THE Proceedings of the Magiſtrates againſt them, And their Apology for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Together with A Memorable example of Gods Iudgements upon ſome of thoſe Perſons ſo proceeded againſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ralph Smith</hi> at the ſigne of the Bible in <hi>Cornhill</hi> neare the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:159091:2"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159091:2"/>
               <head>A Catalogue of ſuch erroneous opinions as were found to have beene brought into <hi>New England,</hi> and ſpread under-hand there, as they were condemned by an Aſſembly of the Churches, at <hi>New Town, Aug.</hi> 30. 1637.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>The Errors 1.</label> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the converſion of a ſinner, which is ſaving and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the faculties of the ſoule, and workings thereof, in things partaining to God, are deſtroyed and made to ceaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The Confutation. 1.</label> This is contrary to the Scripture, which ſpeaketh of the faculties of the ſoule, (as the underſtanding and the will) not as deſtroyed in converſion, but as changed, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.45. Chriſt is ſaid to have opened their underſtandings: <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.18. <hi>Peter</hi> is ſaid to be led whither he would not, therefore he had a will. Againe, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the faculties of the ſoule, is to deſtroy the immortality of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 2.</label> In ſtead of them, the Holy Ghoſt doth come and take place, and doth all the works of thoſe natures, as the faculties of the human nature of Chriſt do.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 2.</label> This is contrary to Scripture which ſpeaketh of God, as ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying our ſoules and ſpirits; 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.23. purging our conſciences, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. refreſhing our memories, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 3.</label> That the love which is ſaid to remain, when faith and hope ceaſe, is the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 3.</label> This is contrary to the Scriptures, which put an expreſſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene the Holy Ghoſt and love, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.6. And if our love were the Holy Ghoſt, we cannot bee ſaid to love God at all, or if wee did, it was, becauſe we were perſonally united to the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 4</label> , 5. That thoſe that bee in Chriſt are not under the Law, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the word, as the rule of life. <hi>Alias,</hi> that the will of God in the Word, or directions thereof, are not the rule whereunto Chriſtians are bound to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelves, to live thereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 4</label> , 5. This is contrary to the Scriptures, which direct us to the Law and to the Teſtimony, <hi>Eſay</hi> 8.20. which alſo ſpeaks of Chriſtians, as not being without Law to God, but under the Law to Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.22.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 6.</label> The example of Chriſts life, is not a patterne according to which men ought to act.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:159091:3"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 6.</label> This poſition (thoſe actions of Chriſt excepted which hee did as God, of as Mediatour, God and Man, or on ſpeciall occaſions, which concerne not us,) is unfound, being contrary to the Scripture, wherein the example of Chriſts life is propounded to Chriſtians as a patterne of imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both by Chriſt and his Apoſtles. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. Learne of mee, for I am meek, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. Bee yee followers of mee, as I am of Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 5.2. Walk in love as Chriſt hath loved us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. Chriſt alſo ſuffered for us, leaving us an example, that yee ſhould follow his ſteps, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.26. Hee that ſaith hee abideth in him, ought ſo to walke, even as hee hath walked.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 7.</label> The new creature, or the new man mentioned in the Goſpell, is not meant of grace, but of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 7.</label> The falſe-hood of this propoſition appeareth from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which firſt propound Chriſt and the new creature as diſtinct one from another, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. If any man bee in Chriſt, hee is a new creature. Secondly, The new man is oppoſed to the old man, the old man is meant of luſts and vices, and not of <hi>Adams</hi> perſon, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.22.24. Therefore the new man is meant of graces and vertues, and not of the perſon of Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.9.10. Thirdly, The new man is expreſſely ſaid to conſiſt in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.25. and to bee renewed in knowledge, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. which are graces, and not Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 8.</label> By love, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13. and by the armour mentioned <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. are meant Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 8.</label> This poſition is neere of kin to the former, but ſecondly, the oppoſite, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. meaneth that love which hee exhorteth Chriſtians to beare one towards another, which if it were meant of Chriſt, hee might bee ſaid to exhort them to beare Chriſt one to another, as well as to love one another, 2. Faith and hope there mentioned, have Chriſt for their object, and if by love bee meant Chriſt, hee had put no more in the latter word, then in the two former. 3. And beſides, it may as well bee ſaid, Faith in love, as Faith in Chriſt, and hope in love, as hope in Chriſt, if that were the meaning. And by armour, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. cannot bee meant Chriſt. Firſt, becauſe two parts of that armour are Faith and Hope, whereof the Scriptures make Chriſt the object: <hi>Col.</hi> 1.5. Beholding the ſted faſtneſſe of your Faith in Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.19. If in this life only wee had hope in Chriſt, &amp;c. now theſe graces, and the object of them cannot bee the ſame. Secondly, a perſon armed with that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, may bee ſaid to bee a ſincere righteous patient Chriſtian, but if by the armour bee meant Chriſt, ſweete predication ſhould have been deſtroyed, and you might more properly ſay, a Chriſtifyed Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 9.</label> The whole letter of the Scripture holds for a covenant of workes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 9.</label> This poſition is unſound, and contrary to the conſtant te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Goſpel, a maine part of the Scriptures which in the letter thereof holds not forth a covenant of works, but of grace, as appeareth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10, 11, 12.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:159091:3"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 10.</label> That God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, may give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſoule, and the ſoule may have true union with Chriſt, true remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins, true marriage and fellowſhip, true ſanctification from the blood of Chriſt, and yet bee an hypocrite.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 10.</label> The word [true] being taken in the ſenſe of the Scriptures, this alſo croſſeth the doctrine of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.24. where righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe are made proper to him, that hath heard and learned the truth, as it is in Jeſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 11.</label> As Chriſt was once made fleſh, ſo hee is now firſt made fleſh in us, ere wee bee carryed to perfection.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 11.</label> Chriſt was once made fleſh, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.14. no other incarnation is recorded, and therefore not to bee believed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 12.</label> Now in the covenant of workes, a legaliſt may attaine the ſame righteouſneſſe for truth, which <hi>Adam</hi> had in innocency before the fall.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 12.</label> Hee that can attaine <hi>Adams</hi> righteouſneſſe in ſincerity, hath his ſin truely mortifyed, but that no legaliſt can have, becauſe true mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is wrought by the covenant of grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. Sin ſhall not have domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over you, for you are not under the Law, but under Grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 13.</label> That there is a new birth under the covenant of workes, to ſuch a kind of righteouſneſſe, as before is mentioned, from which the ſoule muſt bee againe converted, before it can bee made partaker of Gods Kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 13.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Titus</hi> 3.4. where the new birth is made a fruit of Gods love to wards man in Chriſt; of any new birth beſides this, the Scripture ſpeaketh not. It is alſo contrary to 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. where it is made the worke of the Spirit, (that is, the Goſpel) oppoſed to the letter (that is, the Law) to give life; the new birth brings forth the new creature, and the new creature argueth our being in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. It is true indeed Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that are borne againe, muſt bee converted againe, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.3. but that converſion is not from that grace which they have received, but from the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption that ſtill remaines.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 14.</label> That Chriſt workes in the regenerate, as in thoſe that are dead, and not as in thoſe that are alive, or, the regenerate after converſion, are altogether dead to ſpirituall acts.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 14.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11. Yee are alive unto God, in Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1.5. Hee hath quickned us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. Living ſtones, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. The life that I now live.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 15.</label> There is no inherent righteouſneſſe in the Saints, or grace, and graces are not in the ſoules of beleevers, but in Chriſt only.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 15.</label> This is contrary to 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. The unfained faith that dwelt in thee, and dwelt firſt in thy Grandmother, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. partakers of the divine nature; which cannot bee, but by inherent righteouſneſſe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. Stirre up the grace of God which is in thee, <hi>Job.</hi> 1.16. Of his fulneſſe wee all receive grace for grace: but if there be no grace in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159091:4"/>us, wee receive nothing from his fulneſſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. Our inward man is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed day by day, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. with <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.23. wee are changed or renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 16.</label> There is no difference betweene the graces of hypocrites and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, in the kinds of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 16.</label> If this be true, then hypocrites are wiſe, humble, mercifull, pure, &amp;c. and ſo ſhall ſee God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.8. but they are called fooles, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.26. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.1, 2, 3. neither ſhall they ſee God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.51. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.20, 21, 22, 23. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.7, 8, 9. the difference of the grounds, argueth the difference in the kinds of graces.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 17.</label> True poverty of ſpirit doth kill and take away the ſight of grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 17.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.24. Lord, I beleeve, help my unbeleefe: if this were ſo, then poverty of ſpirit ſhould hinder thankfulneſſe, and ſo one grace ſhould hinder another, and the graces of the Spirit ſhould hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the worke of the Spirit, and croſſe the end why hee is given to us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 18.</label> The Spirit doth worke in Hypocrites, by gifts and graces, but in Gods children immediately.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 18.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.15. So did I becauſe of the feare of the Lord: <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.17. <hi>Noah</hi> moved with feare, prepared an Arke.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 19.</label> That all graces, even in the truely regenerate, are mortall and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 19.</label> This is contrary to <hi>John</hi> 4.14. they are graces which flow from a fountaine which ſpringeth up to eternall life, and therefore not fading, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.39.40.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 20.</label> That to call into queſtion whether God be my deare Father, after or upon the commiſſion of ſome hainous ſinnes, (as Murther, Inceſt, &amp;c.) doth prove a man to be in the Covenant of workes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 20.</label> It being ſuppoſed that the doubting here ſpoken of, is not that of finall deſpaire, or the like, but onely that the poſition denyeth a poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of all doubting to a man under a Covenant of grace, this is contrary to Scripture, which ſpeaketh of Gods people under a Covenant of grace, in theſe or other caſes, exerciſed with ſweete doubtings and queſtions: <hi>David</hi> was a juſtified man, (for his ſinnes were pardoned, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.12, 13.) yet his bones waxed old through his roaring all the day long, and the heavineſſe of Gods hand was upon him night and day, and the turning of his moyſture into the drought of Summer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.3, 4. And Gods breaking his bones by with-holding from him the joy of his Salvation; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.8. ſhew that he was exerciſed with ſweete doubts, and queſtions at leaſt, as this poſition ſpeaketh of: and the like may be gathered out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.3, 4. where the holy man <hi>Aſaph,</hi> mentioneth himſelfe, being troubled when he remembred God, and that he was ſo troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, he could not ſpeake nor ſleepe, and expoſtulateth with God, Will the Lord caſt off for ever? and will he be favourable no more? and <hi>verſ.</hi> 6, 7, 8, 9.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159091:4"/>Theſe ſhew that he had at leaſt ſweete doubts, as the poſition mentioneth, and yet he was not thereby proved to be under a Covenant of workes, for he doth afterward confeſſe this to bee his infirmity, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. and receiveth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of former experiences, in former dayes, and his ſongs in the nights, and of Gods former workes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5, 6.10, 11, 12. and he reſumeth his claime of his right in God by vertue of his Covenant, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 21.</label> To be juſtified by faith is to be juſtified by workes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 21.</label> If faith, in this poſition be conſidered not ſimply as a worke, but in relation to its object, this is contrary to the Scripture, that ſo appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ateth Juſtification to faith, as it denieth it to workes, ſetting faith and workes in oppoſition one againſt another in the point of Juſtification, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27. Where is boaſting then? It is excluded. By what Law? by the Law of workes. no, but by the Law of faith, and <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. We conclude, that a man is juſtified by faith without the workes of the Law, and <hi>chap.</hi> 4. 16. Therefore it is by faith, that it may be by grace, compared with <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. To him that worketh is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reckoned not of grace, but of debt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 22.</label> None are to be exhorted to beleeve, but ſuch whom we know to be the elect of God, or to have his Spirit in them effectually.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 22.</label> This is contrary to the Scriptures, which maketh the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion which Chriſt gave his Diſciples in theſe words, Go preach the Goſpel to every creature, he that beleeveth and is baptized ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15.16. where the latter words imply an exhortation to beleeve, and the former words direct that this ſhould not onely be ſpoken to men knowne to be elected, or onely to men effectually called, but to every creature; The Scripture alſo telleth us, that the Apoſtles in all places called upon men to repent, and beleeve the Goſpel, which they might not have done, had this poſition beene true.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 23.</label> We muſt not pray for gifts and graces, but onely for Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 23.</label> This is contrary to Scripture which teacheth us to pray for wiſdome, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.5. and for every grace beſtowed by vertue of the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 36.37. as acknowledging every good gift, and every perfect giving is from above, and commeth downe from the Father of lights. The whole 119. Pſalme, beſides innumerable texts of Scripture, doth abundantly confute this, by ſhewing that the ſervants of God have beene taught by the Spirit of God to pray for every gift and grace needfull for them, and not onely for Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 24.</label> He that hath the ſeale of the Spirit may certainely judge of any perſon, whether he be elected or no.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 24.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29. Secret things belong to God; and ſuch is election of men not yet called.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 25.</label> A man may have all graces and poverty of ſpirit, and yet want Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 25.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.3. Bleſſed are the poore in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: but without Chriſt none can be bleſſed, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.22.24. he that hath righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and true holineſſe, hath learned the truth, as it is in Jeſus, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:159091:5"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 26.</label> The faith that juſtifieth us is in Chriſt, and never had any actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all being out of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 26.</label> This is contrary to Scripture, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.5. Lord encreaſe our faith, <hi>Ergo,</hi> faith was in them, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. faith is ſaid to dwell in ſuch and ſuch perſons, therefore faith was in them, <hi>Eſay</hi> 64.7. No man ſtirres up himſelfe to lay hold upon thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 27.</label> It is incompatible to the Covenant of grace to joyne faith there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 27.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Marke</hi> 16.16. Preach the Goſpel, hee that beleeveth ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Abraham</hi> beleeved, and it was counted to him for righteouſneſſe, and <hi>Abraham</hi> is a patterne to all under the Covenant of grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.24.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 28.</label> To affirme there muſt be faith on mans part to receive the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; is to undermine Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 28.</label> Firſt, Faith is required on mans part to receive the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace, according to theſe Scriptures, <hi>John</hi> 1.12. To as many as received him, even to them that beleeved on his name, <hi>Marke</hi> 16.16. He that beleeveth ſhall be ſaved. Secondly, to affirme there muſt be faith on mans part to receive Chriſt, is not to undermine Chriſt; but to exalt him, according to theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>John</hi> 3.33. He that beleeveth hath put to his ſeale that God is true; and ſo honours Gods truth, which cannot undermine Chriſt; <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.20. but was ſtrong in the faith, giving glory to God, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 29.</label> An hypocrite may have theſe two witneſſes, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.5. that is to ſay, the water and bloud.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 29.</label> No hypocrite can have theſe two witneſſes, water and bloud, that is, true juſtification and ſanctification, for then he ſhould be ſaved, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theſe Scriptures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 30.</label> If any thing may be concluded from the water and bloud, it is rather damnation, then ſalvation.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 30.</label> This is contrary to the Scriptures laſt mentioned.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 31.</label> Such as ſee any grace of God in themſelves, before they have the aſſurance of Gods love ſealed to them are not to be received members of Churches.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 31.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37.38. where the Eunuch ſaw his faith only, and yet was preſently baptized, and therfore by the ſame ground might be admitted.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 32.</label> After the revelation of the ſpirit, neither Devill nor ſinne can make the ſoule to doubt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 32.</label> This poſition ſavours of orrour, elſe <hi>Aſaph.</hi> had not the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Spirit, ſeeing he doubted, (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.13) whether he had not clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his heart in vaine, and that God had forgotten to be gracious; then alſo faith ſhould be perfect which was never found, no not in our father <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 33.</label> To act by vertue of, or in obedience to a command, is legall.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:159091:5"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 33.</label> So is it alſo Evangelicall, the myſtery of the Goſpel is ſaid to be revealed for the obedience of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.25. Alſo the Lord Jeſus is ſaid to be the author of ſalvation to all that obey him, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.9. If we love Chriſt we are to keep his Commandements, <hi>John</hi> 14.29.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 34.</label> We are not to pray againſt all ſinne, becauſe the old man is in us, and muſt be, and why ſhould we pray againſt that which cannot be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyded?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 34.</label> This is contrary to 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5, 23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.7.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 35.</label> The efficacy of Chriſts death is to kill all activity of graces in his members, that he might act all in all.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 35.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. Our old man is crucified with him, that the body of finne might be deſtroyed, that we ſhould not ſerve ſinne: contrary alſo to <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.14. that he might through death deſtroy him, &amp;c. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8. whence we infer, that if Chriſt came to deſtroy the body of ſin, to deſtroy the Devill, to diſſolve the workes of the Devill, then not to kill his owne graces, which are the workes of his owne Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 36.</label> All the activity of a beleever is to act to ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 36.</label> Contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15. as alſo to <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. the ſpirit luſteth againſt the fleſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 37.</label> We are compleatly united to Chriſt, before, or without any faith wrought in us by the Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 37.</label> The terme [united] being underſtood of that ſpirituall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of men unto Chriſt, whereby they come to have life and right to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bleſſings in Chriſt, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12. He that hath the Son hath life: And the terme [compleatly] implying a preſence of all thoſe bands and ligaments and meanes as are required in the word, or are any wayes neceſſary to the making up of the union, we now conceive this aſſertion to be erroneous, contrary to Scripture, that either expreſſely mentioneth faith when it ſpeaketh of this uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. that Chriſt may dwell in your hearts by faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. Chriſt liveth in me by faith; or ever implyeth it in thoſe phraſes that doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe union; as comming to Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 6.35. and eating and drinking Chriſt, <hi>verſ.</hi> 47. compared with <hi>verſ.</hi> 54. having the Sonne, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12. and receiving Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 1.12. and marriage unto Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.32. if there be no dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Chriſt in us, no comming to him, no receiving him, no eating nor drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, no being married to him before and without faith; but the former is true, therefore alſo the latter.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 38.</label> There can be no true cloſing with Chriſt in a promiſe that hath a qualification or condition expreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 38.</label> This opinion we conceive erroneous, contrary to <hi>Eſay</hi> 55.1, 2. Ho! every one that thirſteth come yee to the waters, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. Come to me all yee that are weary and heavy laden, <hi>John</hi> 7.37. If any man thirſt, let him come to me and drinke, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.17. Let him that is athirſt come, <hi>Marke</hi> 1.15. Repent and beleeve the Goſpel: if the word indefinitely be ſanctified, for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159091:6"/>the begetting of faith, if the Goſpel it ſelfe be laid downe in a conditionall promiſe, if the Apoſtles and Prophets, and Chriſt himſelfe, have laid hold up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch promiſes to help to union, and cloſing with himſelfe, then there may be a true cloſing with Chriſt in a promiſe that hath a qualification or condition expreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 39.</label> The due ſearch and knowledge of the holy Scripture, is not a ſafe and ſure way of ſearching and finding Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 39.</label> This is contrary to expreſſe words of Scripture, <hi>John</hi> 5.39. Search the Scriptures, for they teſtifie of me, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.43. To him give all the Prophets witneſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.21. the righteouſneſſe of God witneſſed by the Law and the Prophets, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. To the Law and to the Teſtimony, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. The Bereans were more noble, in that they ſearched the Scriptures daily. If the Prophets give witneſſe to Chriſt, if his righteouſneſſe bee witneſſed by Law and Prophets, and that they bee noble that daily ſearch the Scriptures, and that Chriſt ſo farre alloweth their teſtimony of him, that the Scripture ſaith, there is no light but in and according to them, then the due ſearching and knowledg of Scriptures, is a ſafe way to ſearch Chriſt; but the former is true, therefore alſo the latter.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 40.</label> There is a teſtimony of the Spirit, and voyce unto the Soule, meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly immediate, without any reſpect unto, or concurrence with the word.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 40.</label> This immediate revelation without concurrence with the word, doth not onely countenance but confirme that opinion of Enthuſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, juſtly refuſed by all the Churches, as being contrary to the perfection of the Scriptures, and perfection of Gods wiſedome therein: That which is not revealed in the Scripture, (which is <hi>objectum adaequatum fidei</hi>) is not to be beleeved: but that there is any ſuch revelation, without concurrence with the word, is no where revealed in the Scripture, <hi>Ergo.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. Preſume not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove that which is written. Againe, if there be any immediate Revelation without concurrence of the word, then it cannot be tryed by the word, but wee are bid to try the ſpirits. To the law and Teſtimony, <hi>Eſay</hi> 8.20. to try all things, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.21. So the Bereans, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. and the rule of tryall is the word, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 41.</label> There bee diſtinct feaſons of the workings of the ſeverall Perſons, ſo the ſoule may bee ſaid to bee ſo long under the Fathers, and not the Sons, and ſo long under the Sons work, and not the Spirits.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 41.</label> This expreſſion is not according to the patterne of whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome words, which teacheth a joynt concurrence of all the Perſons, working in every worke that is wrought, ſo that wee cannot ſay, the Father works ſo long and the Son works not, becauſe the ſame worke at the ſame time is common to them both, and to all the three Perſons, as the Father drawes, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.44. ſo the Son ſends his Spirit to convince, and thereby draws, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.7, 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 42.</label> There is no aſſurance true or right, unleſſe it bee with out feare and doubting.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:159091:6"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 42.</label> This is contrary to Scripture; the penman of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77. had true aſſurance, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. and yet hee had doubts and feares of Gods eternall mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 8, 9. The beſt Faith is imperfect and admits infirmity, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.10, 11, 12. Where there is fleſh that doth fight againſt every grace, and act thereof, and is contrary to it, there can bee no grace perfect, <hi>Ergo,</hi> doubting may ſtand with aſſurance, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 43.</label> The Spirit acts moſt in the Saints, when they indevour leaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 43.</label> Reſerving the ſpeciall ſeaſons of Gods preventing grace to his owne pleaſure, In the ordinary conſtant courſe of his diſpenſation, the more wee indevour, the more aſſiſtance and helpe wee find from him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.3, 4, 5. Hee that ſeeks and digs for wiſdome as for treaſure ſhall find it, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.3. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.2. The Lord is with you, while you are with him; If by inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour be meant the uſe of lawfull meanes and Ordinances commanded by God, to ſeeke and find him in, then is it contrary to <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7. Aske, ſeeke, knock, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 44.</label> No created worke can bee a manifeſt ſigne of Gods love.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 44.</label> If created workes flowing from union with Chriſt bee inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, it's againſt <hi>Johns</hi> Epiſtles, and many Scriptures, which make keeping the Commandements, love to the Brethren, &amp;c. evidences of a good eſtate, ſo conſequently of Gods love.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 45.</label> Nothing but Chriſt is an evidence of my good eſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 45.</label> If here Chriſt manifeſting himſelfe in workes of holineſſe, bee excluded, and nothing but Chriſt nakedly revealing himſelfe to faith, bee made an evidence, it is againſt the former Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 46.</label> It is no ſinne in a beleever not to ſee his grace, except he be wilfully blinde.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 46.</label> This is contrary to the Scripture, which makes every tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the Law ſinne, though wilfulneſſe be not annexed; and this croſſeth the worke of the Spirit which ſheweth us the things that are given us of God; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12. and croſſeth alſo that command, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. Prove your faith, and therefore we ought to ſee it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 47.</label> The Seale of the Spirit is limited onely to the immediate witneſſe of the Spirit, and doth never witneſſe to any worke of grace, or to any conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by a Syllogiſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 47.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. to that which our Spirit beares witneſſe, to that the Spirit of God beares witneſſe, for they beare a joynt witneſſe, as the words will have it: but our Spirits beare witneſſe to a worke of grace, namely that beleevers are the children of God, <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 48.</label> That conditionall promiſes are legall.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 48.</label> Contrary to <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>Matthew</hi> 5.3. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 49.</label> We are not bound to keepe a conſtant courſe of Prayer in our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, or privately, unleſſe the Spirit ſtirre us up thereunto.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 49.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.18. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:159091:7"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 50.</label> It is poverty of ſpirit, when wee have grace, yet to ſee wee have no grace in our ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 50.</label> The weake beleever <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.24. was poore in ſpirit, yet ſaw his own Faith weak though it were. <hi>Peter</hi> when hee was brought to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty of ſpirit by the bitter experience of his pride, hee ſaw the true love hee had unto Chriſt, and appealed to him therein, <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.15. <hi>Paul</hi> was leſſe then the leaſt of all Saints in his owne eyes, therefore poore in ſpirit, yet ſaw the grace of God, by which hee was that he was, and did what hee did, and was truly nothing in his own eyes, when hee had ſpoken of the beſt things hee had received and done, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.18. If it bee poverty of the ſpirit to ſee no grace in our ſelves, then ſhould poverty of ſpirit croſſe the office of the Spirit, which is to reveale unto us, and make us to ſee what God gives us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.10, 11, 12. then it ſhould make us ſinne, or croſſe the will of God, which is, that wee ſhould not bee ignorant of the gracious workings of Chriſt in us from the power of his death and reſurrection, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. Know yee not, &amp;c. then would it deſtroy a great duty of Chriſtian thankfulneſſe, in, and for all the good things which God vouchſafeth us, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.18.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 51.</label> The ſoule need not to goe out to Chriſt for freſh ſupply, but it is acted by the Spirit inhabiting.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 51.</label> Though wee have the Spirit acting and inhabiting us, this hinders not, but I may and need goe out to Chriſt for freſh ſupply of Grace, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.16. Of whoſe fulneſſe wee have all received, and grace for grace; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8. <hi>Paul</hi> ſought thrice to Chriſt for freſh ſupply; <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. Looke unto Chriſt the Authour and finiſher of our faith.</p>
               <p>Wee muſt looke up to the hils from whence commeth our helpe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.16. by whom all the body receiveth increaſe, and to the edifying of it ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 52.</label> It is legal to ſay, wee act in the ſtrength of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 52.</label> This is contrary to the Scriptures, the Goſpel bids us bee ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.10 and bee ſtrong in the grace that is in Chriſt Jeſus, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, I can do all things through Chriſt that ſtrengtheneth me, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. and that was not le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall ſtrength.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 53.</label> No Miniſter can teach one that is anoynted by the Spirit of Chriſt, more then hee knowes already unleſſe it be in ſome circumſtances.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 53.</label> This is alſo contrary to Scripture, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. It is God that ſtabliſheth us with you, &amp;c. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. and 4.12.14. The <hi>Corinthians</hi> and <hi>Epheſians,</hi> were anoynted and ſealed, and yet were taught more of <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtles then only in ſome circumſtances.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 54.</label> No Miniſter can bee an inſtrument to convey more of Chriſt unto another, then hee by his own experience hath come unto.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 54.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12. the weakeſt Miniſter may edify the ſtrongeſt Chriſtian which hath more experience then himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 55.</label> A man may have true Faith of dependance, and yet not bee juſtifyed.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:159091:7"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 55.</label> This is contrary to the Scripture, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.39. Al believers are juſtifyed, but they that have true faith of dependance are believers, therefore juſtifyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 56.</label> A man is not effectually converted till hee hath full aſſurance.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 56.</label> This is croſſe to the Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.10. wherein wee ſee that a man may truely feare God (therefore truely converted) and yet walke in darkneſſe, without cleare evidence; or full aſſurance.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 57.</label> To take delight in the holy ſervice of God, is to go a whoring from God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 57.</label> No Scripture commands us to go a whoring from God, but firſt, the Scripture commands us to delight in the ſervice of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 100.2. Serve the Lord with gladneſſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13. Thou ſhalt call the Sabbath thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, <hi>Ergo.</hi> Secondly, God loves not ſuch as go a whoring from him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. <hi>ult.</hi> but God loves a cheerful ſerver of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. Therefore, ſuch as ſerve him cheerfully, do not thereby go a whoring from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 58.</label> To help my faith, and comfort my conſcience in evill houres, from former experience of Gods grace in mee, is not a way of grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 58.</label> What the Saints have done and found true comfort in, that is a way of grace; but they did help their faith, and comfort their conſcience from former evidences of Gods grace in them: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.5, 6, 11. I conſidered the dayes of old, and called to remembrance my ſongs in the night; and by this raiſed hee up his faith, as the latter part of the <hi>Pſalm</hi> ſheweth; and this was in evil houres, <hi>ver.</hi> 2, 3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. This is our rejoycing, that in ſimplicity and godly pureneſſe, wee have had our converſation, and this was in ſad houres <hi>ver.</hi> 4, 5, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Job</hi> 35.10. None ſaith, Where is God that made mee, which giveth ſongs in the night? here the not attending to former conſolation, is counted a ſinful neglect.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 59.</label> A man may not bee exhorted to any duty, becauſe hee hath no power to do it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 59.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12, 13. Work out your ſalvation &amp;c. For it is God that worketh in you both the will and the deed, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.14. A wake thou that ſleepeſt, ſo 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 60.</label> A man may not prove his election by his vocation, but his voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by his election.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 60.</label> This is contrary to 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. knowing your election, becauſe our Goſpel came unto you, not in word only, but in power, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13, 14. God hath elected you to life, through ſanctification of the Spirit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto hee hath called you by our Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 61.</label> All Doctrines, Revelations and Spirits, muſt be tried by Chriſt the word, rather then by the Word of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 61.</label> This aſſertion of it intends to exclude the word, we conceive it contrary to <hi>Eſay</hi> 8.20. <hi>John</hi> 5.39. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. alſo to 2 <hi>John</hi> 4.1, 2. Trye the ſpirits, every ſpirit that confeſſeth that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, &amp;c.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:159091:8"/>where Spirits and Doctrines confeſſing that Chriſt is come in the fleſh, are made diſtinct from Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 62.</label> It is a dangerous thing to cloſe with Chriſt in a promiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 62.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Joh</hi> 7.37. If Chriſt in theſe places invite men to come unto him, and bids them incline and hearken, and tells them their Soules ſhall live, and they ſhall drinke and be refreſhed by hm, and by theſe promiſes encourageth them to cloſe with him, then it is no dangerous thing to cloſe with him in a promiſe, it is no danger to obey a Command of God: but we are commanded to beleeve the Goſpell, <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.15, 1. the promiſe being a part of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 63.</label> No better is the evidence from the two witneſſes of water and blood, mentioned 1 <hi>John.</hi> 5.6, 7, 8. then mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> and the Souldiers that ſhed Chriſts bloud, and theſe might have drunke of it; poore eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 63.</label> Then what God hath ordained or made an evidence, is no better then what he hath not made, then Chriſt loſeth his end in comming by water and blood, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. then the Spirit ſhould agree no better with the witneſſe of water and bloud, then it doth with Mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> and the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: but the Spirit doth agree with the water and the bloud, and not with the other, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7. Theſe three agree in one.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 64.</label> A man muſt take no notice of his ſinne, nor of his repentance for his ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 64.</label> This is contrary to <hi>David,</hi> whoſe ſinnes were ever before him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. hee conſidered his wayes (and the evill of them) that he might turne his feete to Gods Teſtimonies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 59. If we confeſſe our ſinnes, he is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and juſt, &amp;c. If we ſay we have not ſinned we make him a lyar, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8, 9, 10. <hi>Job</hi> tooke notice of ſinne and of his repentance, I abhorre my ſelfe and repent in duſt and aſhes, <hi>Job</hi> 42 6. <hi>David</hi> ſeeth, and ſaith, I am ſorry for my ſinnes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38 28. <hi>Solomons</hi> penitent muſt know the Plague in his heart, that is, his finne and the puniſhment thereof, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8 38.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 65.</label> The Church in admitting members is not to looke to holineſſe of life, or Teſtimony of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 65.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7. and the inſcriptions of divers Epiſtles, being directed to Saints, and Saints by calling, and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 33. Churches of the Saints, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. the members there, were ſaid to repent before they were admitted, and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. the inceſtuous perſon ſhould not then have beene caſt out for want of holineſſe, and <hi>Paul</hi> could not be received into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion without Teſtimony, <hi>Acts</hi> 9 26.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 66.</label> To lay the brethren under a Covenant of works, hurts not, but tends to much good to make men looke the better to their evidences.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 66.</label> If that bee done ungroundedly, it is contrary to <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.20. where woe is pronounced to ſuch as call good evill, &amp;c. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.22. that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:159091:8"/>make ſuch hearts ſad, as the Lord would not have ſadded; and it is againſt the rule of the Covenant, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. beſides, it may trench upon the devils office, in accuſing the Brethren, and then it will be good to tell untruth, good to breake houſe and Church Communion, then good to break neareſt relations, then good to bite one another, and good to offend the little ones, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 67.</label> A man cannot evidence his juſtification by his ſanctification, but he muſt needs build upon his ſanctification, and truſt to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 67.</label> Firſt, this is contrary to 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.18, 19. where the holy Ghoſt ſaith, that by unfained and hearty love we may have aſſurance, and yet neither there nor any where elſe would have us truſt to our ſanctification, ſo <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. He that doth righteouſneſſe is righteous, as he is righteous. Secondly, if poverty of ſpirit, which emptieth us of all confidence in our ſelves, may evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence a mans juſtification without truſting to it, then may ſanctification with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out truſting to it; but the former is true, therefore alſo the latter. Thirdly, if it be an ordinance of God to evidence our juſtification by our ſanctification, then we may doe this without truſting to it: but that is apparent from, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 68.</label> Faith juſtifies an unbeleever, that is, that faith that is in Chriſt, juſtifieth me that have no faith in my ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 68.</label> This is contrary to <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.4. For if the juſt ſhall live by his faith, then that faith that juſtifies is not in Chriſt. So <hi>John</hi> 3. ult. He that beleeveth not, the wrath of God abideth on him: it is not anothers faith will ſave me.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 69.</label> Though a man can prove a gracious worker in: himſelfe, and Chriſt to be the authour of it, if thereby he will prove Chriſt to be his, this is but a ſandy foundation.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 69.</label> This is contrary to theſe Scriptures, <hi>John</hi> 14.21. and 28. He that keepeth my commandements, is he that loveth me, and he that loveth me, ſhall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and will ſhew my ſelfe unto him, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.14. We know that we have paſſed from death to life, becauſe we love the brethren, and 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12. He that hath the Sonne hath life: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that can prove that he hath ſpirituall life, may aſſure himſelfe that hee hath Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 70.</label> Frequency or length of holy duties or trouble of conſcience for neglect thereof, are all ſignes of one under a Covenant of workes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 70.</label> This is contrary to theſe Scriptures, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. Be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant alwayes in the worke of the Lord: if the faithfull in Chriſt Jeſus be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to abound alwayes in the worke of the Lord, that is, holy duties, then frequency in holy duties is no ſigne of one under a Covenant of workes: but the former is true, therefore alſo the latter; as alſo 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17.18. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.17. Evening and morning and noone will I pray and make a noyſe, and he will heare me; and elſewhere, Seven times a day doe I praiſe thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.146. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2. So alſo contrary is the third branch to theſe Scriptures, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.8.11.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:159091:9"/>the Corinthians were troubled in conſcience, and ſorrowed that they had neglected the holy duties of Church cenſure towards the inceſtuous perſon, and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.7. and 8. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.19. I doe not the good I would, which he lamenteth and complaineth of.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 71.</label> The immediate revelation of my good eſtate, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Scriptures, is as cleare to me, as the voyce of God from Heaven to <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 71.</label> This is contrary to <hi>John</hi> 14.26. He ſhall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, &amp;c. whence we reaſon thus. If the Spirit reveale nothing without concurrence of the Word, then this revelation of the Spirit without reſpect to the Word is not cleare, nor to be truſted: but the Spirit doth reveale nothing, but with reſpect to the Word, for <hi>John</hi> 14.26. If the office of the Spirit be to teach and to bring to remembrance the things that Chriſt hath taught us, <hi>Eſay</hi> 8.20. what ever ſpirit ſpeakes not according to this Word, there is no light there.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 72.</label> It is a fundamentall and ſoule-damning errour to make ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation an evidence of juſtification.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 72.</label> This is contrary to theſe Scriptures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. They that walke after the Spirit, are freed from condemnation; and are in Chriſt, and ſo juſtified: ſo 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.10. In this are the children of God knowne, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 73.</label> Chriſts worke of grace can no more diſtinguiſh betweene a Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite and a Saint, then the raine that fals from Heaven betweene the juſt and the unjuſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 73.</label> This propoſition being generall includes all gracious works, and being ſo taken is contradicted in the parable of the ſower, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.20.21, 22. where the good ground is diſtinguiſhed from the ſtony by this, that it brings forth fruit with patience, ſo <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.9. there is ſomething better in the Saints then thoſe common gifts which are found in Hypocrites.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 74.</label> All verball Covenants, or Covenants expreſſed in words, as Church Couenants, vowes, &amp;c. are Covenants of workes, and ſuch as ſtrike men off from Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 74.</label> Firſt, this is contrary to Scripture, <hi>Eſay</hi> 44 5. One ſhall ſay, I am the Lords, another ſhall call himſelfe by the name of the God of <hi>Jacob: Rom.</hi> 10.10. With the mouth confeſſion is made to ſalvation. Secondly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to reaſon, for then the Covenant of grace is made a Covenant of workes, by the writing, reading, and preaching of the ſame, for they are verball expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Covenant on Gods part, as Church Covenants verbally expreſſe our cloſing herewith.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 75.</label> The Spirit giveth ſuch full and cleare evidence of my good eſtate, that I have no need to be tried by the fruits of ſanctification, this were to light a candle to the Sun.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 75.</label> This opinion taken in this ſenſe, that after the Spirit hath teſtified a mans good eſtate, the perſon need not to be tried by the fruit of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:159091:9"/>is contrary to the ſcope of the whole firſt Epiſtle of Saint <hi>John,</hi> where variety of arguments are propounded to all beleevers in common, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.13. to diſtinguiſh the perſons of beleevers from unbeleevers; the water is annexed to the Spirit and bloud, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 76.</label> The Devill and nature may be cauſe of a gracious worke.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 76.</label> The words are unſavoury, and the poſition unſound, for taking [gracious] according to the language of the Scripture, gracious words, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.22. Let your ſpeech be gracious, gracious words are ſuch as iſſue from the ſaving grace of Chriſts Spirit indwelling in the ſoule, which neither the Devill, nor nature is able to produce, for Chriſt profeſſeth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.3, 4. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me yee can doe nothing, nothing truly gracious, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. What ever is borne of the fleſh is fleſh, and <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. In my fleſh dwels no good, (truly ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and gracious) <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. Every imagination of the thoughts of a mans heart, are evill, and that continually; Beſides, the Devill is that evill and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked one, onely wickedneſſe, an adverſary to Gods grace and glory, that which is contrary to corrupt nature, and the helliſh nature of Satan, and above the power of both, they cannot be the cauſes of gracious works.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 77.</label> Sanctification is ſo farre from evidencing a good eſtate that it darkens it rather, and a man may more clearely ſee Chriſt, when he ſeeth no ſanctification then when he doth, the darker my ſanctification is, the brighter is my juſtification.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 77.</label> This is contrary to the Scripture of truth, which rather giveth the name of light to ſanctification and holineſſe, and even for this uſe, to cleare our juſtification, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.6, 7. For the holy Ghoſt concludes as from a cleare and infallible promiſe, and propoſition, that if we walke in the light, as he is in the light, then doth the bloud of Chriſt cleanſe us from all ſinne; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that then and thereby it appeareth that it is done: as by the contrary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holineſſe, and unholy walking is like darkneſſe, which obſcureth all the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſumption flouriſhes and hopes of an unregenerate man, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. For this purpoſe, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.8. the water of ſanctification is made a witneſſe, now the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a witneſſe is not to darken and obſcure matters in queſtion, but to cleare them, and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.10, 11, 12. when <hi>David</hi> ſaw his heart ſo uncleane, and his ſpirit ſo altogether out of order, his juſtification was not then brighter, for then he ſhould have had the joy of his ſalvation more full, and not ſo to ſinke as that he begs it might be reſtored to him, as implying, that his joy for the preſent was wanting to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 78.</label> God hath given ſixe witneſſes, three in Heaven and three in earth, to beget and build juſtifying faith upon.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 78.</label> This expreſſion anſwers not the patterne of wholeſome words, for if this poſition be taken thus, God hath given all theſe ſixe witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes both to beget and alſo to build juſtifying faith upon, it is contrary to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for God hath not given all theſe fixe witneſſes to beget juſtifying faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the water of ſanctification, which is one of the ſixe, doth not goe before
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:159091:10"/>juſtifying faith, but followeth after it, for our hearts are juſtified by faith, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 79.</label> If a member of a Church be unſatisfied with any thing in the Church, if he expreſſe his offence, whether he hath uſed all meanes to convince the Church or no, he may depart.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 79.</label> Contrary to the rule of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. If thy brother offend (convictingly) admoniſh; whence it is evident, that in our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage towards a private brother we muſt convince him, before admoniſh him, much leſſe ſeparate from him. Therefore our carriage towards the whole Church muſt upon greater reaſon be with like prudence, and tenderneſſe; whence the argument followes thus. An offence taken before conviction will not beare an admonition, much leſſe ſeparation from a brother or Church: but the offence in the queſtion propounded is ſuch, <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 80.</label> If a man thinke he may edifie better in another congregation then in his owne, that is ground enough to depart ordinarily, from word, ſeales, faſtings, feaſtings, and all adminiſtrations in his owne Church, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the offence of the Church, often manifeſted to him for ſo doing.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 80.</label> It is contrary to the condition and ſtation of a member of the body in which he ſtands, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.27. A member muſt not put it ſelfe from the body upon its owne thoughts; as the admiſſion of a member was by the conſent of the whole, ſo likewiſe muſt his diſmiſſion be. It is contrary alſo to the duty of a member, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.16. there muſt be an effectuall working in every part for the edification of the whole which this departure from the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of all the holy ordinances in the Church will neceſſarily hinder. It is contrary alſo to the good of the whole Church, and the rule which the Lord hath appointed for the preſervation thereof, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 33. God is not the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of confuſion, and therefore not of this practiſe which will certainly bring it, for if one member upon theſe his imaginations may depart, why may not ten, yea twenty, yea an hundred? Why may not the Paſtor upon ſuch grounds leave his people, as well as they him, conſidering the tye is equall on both parts?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Error 81.</label> Where faith is held forth by the Miniſtery, as the condition of the covenant of grace on mans part, as alſo evidencing juſtification by ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and the activity of faith, in that Church there is not ſufficient bread.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 81.</label> This poſition ſeemeth to deny faith to be a condition at all, or at all active, and ſo if condition in this place ſignifie a qualification in man wrought by the holy Ghoſt, without which the promiſes doe not belong to men, this is contrary to Scripture, for <hi>John</hi> 6.48. Chriſt is the bread of life, and yet in the ſame chapter faith is held out as a condition of the covenant by the Miniſtery of Chriſt himſelfe; and the activity of it is held forth in theſe words, Verily I ſay unto you, unleſſe yee eate the fleſh, and drinke the bloud of the Sonne of man, you have no life in you, and who ſo eateth, &amp;c. As for the lawfulneſſe of evidencing juſtification by ſanctification (if it be underſtood
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:159091:10"/>of that ſanctification which is by faith in Chriſt) it is contrary to the intent of the whole Epiſtle of <hi>John,</hi> beſides many other places of Scripture which yet hold forth bread ſufficient (if by ſufficient is meant that doctrine, which in its right uſe is wholſome and good food) for it was written that their joy might be full; yet the evidencing of juſtification by ſanctification is expreſſely held forth <hi>chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. where he ſaith, If we walke in the light, as Chriſt is in the light, we have fellowſhip one with another, and the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſinne; by walking in the light, in oppoſition to walking in darkneſſe ſpoken of before, <hi>verſe</hi> 6. Sanctification is evidently meant, and this is expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly noted to be an evidence of our good condition, when it is ſaid, if we ſo walke, the bloud of Chriſt cleanſeth us from all finne.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Errour 82.</label> A Miniſter muſt not pray nor preach againſt any errour, unleſſe he declare in the open Congregation, upon any members enquiry, the names of them that hold them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Confutation 82.</label> This is contrary to Scriptures, which teach Miniſters to pray and preach againſt all errours by whom ſoever they be held, when it calleth them Watchmen and Stewards, in whom faithfulneſſe is required in all adminiſtrations: yet withall it enjoyneth them if a brother ſinne not openly, to admoniſh him in ſecret, firſt betweene them two alone, and afterwards in the preſence of two or three witneſſes, and after that (and not before) to bring the matter to the Church, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15, 16, 17.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Vnſavoury ſpeeches confuted.</head>
               <head type="sub">Theſe that follow were judged by the Aſſembly aforeſaid, as unſafe ſpeeches.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>TO ſay that we are juſtified by faith is an unſafe ſpeech, we muſt ſay we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwer</label> 1. Faiſe, for the conſtant language of the Scripture is not unſafe; but we are juſtified by faith, is the conſtant language of the Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. being juſtified by faith; the righteouſneſſe of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.31, 32. Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by faith, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3, 9, 10.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The diſtinct phraſe of the Scripture uſed in diſtinguiſhing Legall and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall righteouſneſſe is no unſafe ſpeech, but ſuch is this, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.31, 32. <hi>Iſrael</hi> found not righteouſneſſe, becauſe they ſought it of the Law, and not of, or by faith, ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.5, 6. The righteouſneſſe of faith, ſaith thus, &amp;c. The Apoſtle makes theſe two ſo directly oppoſite, as <hi>membra dividentia,</hi> or contrary ſpecies, that there is no danger one ſhould be taken for another, but that it's ſo ſafe, as that he that affirmes the one denies the other: yea in the moſt exact ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion that ever <hi>Paul</hi> made, to exclude whatſoever might be unſafe towards a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:159091:11"/>mans juſtification, you have this phraſe, yea twice in the ſame verſe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. not having mine owne righteouſneſſe, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt; And againe, The righteouſneſſe which is of God by faith (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is no unſafe ſpeech, yea it muſt be ſaid on the contrary from thoſe grounds, that to ſay a man is juſtified before faith, or without faith is unſafe, as contrary to the language of the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>And for the ſecond part, that we muſt ſay, we are juſtified by Chriſt, it is true ſo farre, as that it cannot be denyed, nor is it unſound or unſafe at all ſo to ſpeake, but if it meane a muſt of neceſſity alwayes, or onely ſo to ſpeake as it is here ſet in oppoſition to the phraſe of being juſtified by faith, then it is utterly falſe, for as much as the Scripture leades us along in the way of other expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ordinarily, and the Apoſtle gives us the truth of doctrine and ſoundneſſe of phraſe together, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3. Chriſt is the end of the Law for righteouſneſſe to every one that beleeveth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>To evidence juſtification by ſanctification, or graces, ſavours of Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwer.</label> Not ſo. 1. <hi>Rome</hi> acknowledgeth not juſtification in our common fenſe, <hi>Scil.</hi> by righteouſneſſe imputed. 2. <hi>Rome</hi> demies evidencing of our ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification and peace with God, and teacheth a doctrine of doubting, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth that a man cannot know what God will doe with him for life or death, unleſſe by ſpeciall revelation, which is not ordinary. But if they meane old <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Pauls Rome,</hi> to which he wrote, it's true, that it ſavours of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that they received, as appeareth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. All things co-worke for good (the evill of every evill being taken away, which is a point of juſtification, and this is propounded under the evidence of the love of God) to them that love him, becauſe <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2.9.13.14. the evidencing of our being in Chriſt, freedome from condemnation, and adoption is proſecuted by arguments from ſanctification, as by having the ſpirit, being led by the ſpirit, walking after the ſpirit, mortifying the deeds of the fleſh by the ſpirit: and if hereto were added the doctrine of Saint <hi>John</hi> ſo abundant this way in his firſt Epiſtle (whereof I have already made mention) I doubt not, but it was the faith of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> that then was, ſo that the ſpeech is unſavoury, and caſting a foule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſion upon a good thing expreſſed in the Scriptures, but as for the point it ſelfe, that is included, we referre it to its place, to be diſcuſſed, when it is right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtated.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>If I be holy I am never the better accepted of God, if I be unholy I am never the worſe, this I am ſure of, be that hath electodome muſt ſave me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> Theſe words ſavour very ill, and reliſh of a careleſſe and ungraclous ſpirit, for howſoever we grant that our acceptation unto juſtification is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in and through Chriſt the ſame in Gods account, yet this expreſſion im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, that though a mans converſation be never ſo holy and gracious, yet hee can expect never the more manifeſtation of Gods kindneſſe and love to him, contrary to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. <hi>ult.</hi> To him that orders his converſation aright I will ſhew the ſalvation of God, and <hi>John</hi> 14.21. It implies ſecondly, that though a mans
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:159091:11"/>converſation be never ſo vile and ſenſuall, yet he neede not feare nor expect any further expreſſion of Gods diſpleaſure and anger to breake forth againſt him, or withdrawings of his favour from him, contrary to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.8.11, 12. where God breakes <hi>Davids</hi> bones for his ſinne, and <hi>Jonah</hi> 2.4. <hi>Jonah</hi> was as one caſt out of Gods preſence, and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.2. If you forſake him hee will forſake you: And in a word it imports, as if God neither loved righteouſneſſe, nor ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wickedneſſe, contrary to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.6 7. and did take no delight in the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of his people, contrary to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.11. The Lord delighteth in thoſe that feare him, &amp;c. As concerning the laſt clauſe, he that hath elected me muſt ſave me: it is true, the foundation of Gods election remaineth ſure, yet it is as true, that whom he chooſeth, he purpoſeth to bring to Salvation, through San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of the Spirit, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>If Chriſt will let me ſinne, let him looke to it, upon his honour be it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> This retorts the Lords words upon himſelfe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.23, 24 Keepe thine heart, &amp;c. Ponder thy paths, &amp;c. and therefore no leſſe blaſphemous, and is contrary to the profeſſed practiſe of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 18 23. I was upright before him, and kept my ſelfe from mine iniquity: The latter clauſe puts the cauſe of Gods diſhonour upon himſelfe, no leſſe blaſphemous then the former, and contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.23. where the diſhonouring of God is laid upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Here is a great ſtirre about graces and looking to hearts, but give me Chriſt, I ſeeke not for graces, but for Chriſt, I ſeeke not for promiſes, but for Chriſt, I ſeeke not for ſanctification, but for Chriſt, tell not me of meditation and duties, but tell me of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> 1. This ſpeech ſeemeth to make a flat oppoſition betweene Chriſt and his graces, contrary to that in <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.16. Of his fulneſſe we all received, and grace for grace; and betweene Chriſt and his promiſes, contrary to <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13, 14. Chriſt was made a curſe that wee might receive the promiſe of the Spirit, and <hi>Luke</hi> 1.70. with 74. And betwixt Chriſt and all holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, contrary to <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. and therefore hold forth expreſſions not agreeing to wholeſome doctrine.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>A living faith, that hath living fruits, may grow from the living Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> This whole ſpeech is utterly croſſe to the ſound forme of words re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. Hold faſt the forme of ſound words. 1. That a Hypocrite may have a living Law, is contrary to <hi>James</hi> 2.17. where the hypocrites faith is called a dead faith. 2. That a hypocrite may bring forth living fruite, is contrary to that, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. 3. That all this growes from a living law, contrary to 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 6. where the law is called a killing letter, and to <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.21. If there had beene a law which could have given life, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>I may know I am Chriſts, not becauſe I doe crucifie the luſts of the fleſh, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I doe not crucifie them, but beleeve in Chriſt that crucified my luſts for me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> 1. The phraſe is contrary to the Scripture language, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24. They that are Chriſts, have crucified the fleſh with the affections and luſts. 2. It ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:159091:12"/>of the fleſh, for theſe three things may ſeeme to be expreſſed in it. 1. If Scripture makes not oppoſite, but ſubordinate, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. I through the Spirit crucifie the fleſh. 2. That if I doe not crucifie my luſts, then there is an open and free way of looking to Chriſt, contrary to the Scripture, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.8. Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God, both in boldneſſe of faith here, and fruition hereafter, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. Let every one that names the Lord Jeſus, depart from iniquity. 3. That beleeving in Chriſt, may eaſe me from endeavouring to crucifie my luſts in my owne perſon; which is ſo groſſe, that it needes no more confutation then to name it. 4. The ſafe ſenſe that may be poſſibly intended in ſuch a ſpeech is this, If I crucifie the fleſh in my own ſtrength, it is no ſafe evidence of my being in Chriſt, but if renouncing my ſelfe, I cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the fleſh in the ſtrength of Chriſt, applying his death by faith, it is a ſafe evidence of my being in Chriſt: but this ſenſe conveighed in theſe words, is to conveigh wholeſome doctrine in an unwholeſome Channell, and a darkening and loſing the truth in an unſavoury expreſſion.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Peter <hi>more leaned to a Covenant of workes then</hi> Paul, Pauls <hi>doctrine was more for free grace then</hi> Peters.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> To oppoſe theſe perſons and the doctrine of theſe two Apoſtles of Chriſt, who were guided by one and the ſame Spirit in preaching and penning thereof, (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. Holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. All Scripture is given by inſpiration of God) in ſuch a point as the Covenant of workes and grace, is little leſſe then blaſphemy.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>If Chriſt be my Sanctiflcation, what neede I looke to any thing in my ſelfe, to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence my juſtification?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> This poſition is therefore unſound, becauſe it holds forth Chriſt to be my ſanctification, ſo as that I neede not looke to any inherent holineſſe in my ſelfe; whereas Chriſt is therefore ſaid to be our ſanctification, becauſe he workes ſanctification in us, and we daily ought to grow up in him, by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving new ſupply and increaſe of grace from his fulneſſe, according to 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. Grow in grace and in the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:159091:12"/>
               <head>The proceedings of the Generall Court holden at <hi>New Towne in the Maſſachuſets in New England, Octob.</hi> 2. 1637. Againſt Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> and other erroneous and ſeditious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for their diſturbances of the publick peace.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the Aſſembly of the Churches had confuted and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned moſt of thoſe new opinions which were ſprung up amongſt us, and Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> had in publique view conſented with the reſt, yet the leaders in thoſe erroneous wayes would not give in, but ſtood ſtill to maintain their new light, which they had boaſted of, and that the difference was ſtill as wide as before, <hi>viz.</hi> as great as between heaven and hell: Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> alſo continued his preaching after his former manner, and Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon</hi> her wonted meetings and exerciſes, and much offence was ſtill given by her, and others in going out of the ordinary aſſemblies, when Mr <hi>Wal.</hi> began any exerciſe; and ſome of the meſſengers of the Church of <hi>Boſton,</hi> had contemptuouſly withdrawn themſelves from the generall Aſſembly, with profeſſed diſlike of their proceedings, and many evidences brake forth of their diſcontented and turbulent ſpirits; it was conceived by the Magiſtrates, and others of the Countrey, that the means which had been uſed, proving un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectuall, the caſe was now deſperate, and the laſt remedy was to bee applyed, and that without further delay, leſt it ſhould bee attempted too late, when fitter opportunity might bee offered for their advantage, as they had boaſted, and did certainly expect upon the returne of ſome of their chiefe ſupporters, who by a ſpeciall providence were now abſent from them: And for this end the generall Court being aſſembled in the ordinary courſe, it was determined to begin with theſe troublers of our peace, and to ſuppreſſe them by the civill authority, whereunto there was a faire occaſion offered upon a ſeditious writing, which had been delivered into the Court in <hi>March,</hi> when Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> was convict of ſedition, &amp;c. under the hands of more than threeſcore of them, and intitled <hi>A Remonſtrance or Petition,</hi> the Contents whereof were as followeth:</p>
               <p>Wee whoſe names are under written (have diligently obſerved this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Courts proceedings againſt our deare and reverend brother in Chriſt, Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> now under cenſure of the Court, for the truth of Chriſt) wee do humbly beſeech this honourable Court to accept this Remonſtrance and Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ours, in all due ſubmiſſion tendred to your Worſhips.</p>
               <p>For firſt, whereas our beloved Brother Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> is cenſured for contempt, by the greater part of this honoured Court, wee deſire your Worſhips to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſincere intention of our Brother to promote your end in the day of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:159091:13"/>Faſt, for whereas wee do perceive your principal intention the day of Faſt look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed chiefely at the publick peace of the Churches, our Reverend Brother did to his beſt ſtrength, and as the Lord aſſiſted him, labour to promote your end, and therefore indevoured to draw us neerer unto Chriſt, the head of our union, that ſo wee might bee eſtabliſhed in peace, which wee conceive to bee the true way, ſanctifyed of God, to obtaine your end, and therfore deſerves no ſuch cenſure as wee conceive.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Whereas our deare Brother is cenſured of ſedition; wee beſeech your Worſhips to conſider, that either the perſon condemned muſt bee culpable of ſome ſeditious fact, or his doctrine muſt bee ſeditious, or muſt breed ſedition in the hearts of his hearers or elſe wee know not upon what grounds hee ſhould bee cenſured. Now to the firſt, wee have not heard any that have witneſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our brother for any ſeditious fact. Secondly, neither was the doctrine it ſelfe, being no other but the very expreſſions of the Holy Ghoſt himſelfe, and therefore cannot juſtly be branded with ſedition. Thirdly, if you look at the effects of his Doctrine upon the hearers, it hath not ſtirred up ſedition in us, not ſo much as by accident; wee have not drawn the ſword, as ſometimes <hi>Peter</hi> did, raſhly, neither have wee reſcued our innocent Brother, as ſometimes the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did <hi>Jonathan,</hi> and yet they did not ſeditiouſly. The Covenant of free Grace held forth by our Brother, hath taught us rather to become hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſuppliants to your Worſhips, and if wee ſhould not prevaile, wee would rather with patience give our cheekes to the ſmiters. Since therefore the Teacher, the Doctrine, and the hearers bee moſt free from ſedition (as wee conceive) wee humbly beſeech you in the name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, your Judge and ours, and for the honour of this Court, and the proceedings thereof, that you will bee pleaſed either to make it appeare to us, and to all the world, to whom the knowledge of all theſe things will come, wherein the ſedition lies, or elſe acquit our Brother of ſuch a cenſure.</p>
               <p>Further, wee beſeech you remember the old method of Satan, the ancient e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of Free Grace, in all ages of the Churches, who hath raiſed up ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies againſt the faithfull Prophets of God, <hi>Eliah</hi> was called the troubler of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.17, 18. <hi>Amos</hi> was charged for conſpiracy, <hi>Amos</hi> 7.10. <hi>Paul</hi> was counted a peſtilent fellow, or moover of ſedition, and a ring-leader of a Sect, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.5. and Chriſt himſelfe, as well as <hi>Paul,</hi> was charged to bee a Teacher of New Doctrine, <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Acts</hi> 17 19. Now wee beſeech you conſider, whether that old ſerpent work not after his old method, even in our daies.</p>
               <p>Further, wee beſeech you conſider the danger of medling againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.14.15. for what yee do unto them, the Lord Jeſus takes as done unto himſelfe; if you hurt any of his members, the head is very ſenſible of it: for ſo ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, Hee that toucheth you toucheth the apple of mine eye, <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.8. And better a mill-ſtone were hanged about our necks, and that wee were caſt into the ſea, then that wee ſhould offend any
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:159091:13"/>of theſe little ones, which beleeve on him, <hi>Matthew</hi> 18.6.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, wee beſeech you conſider, how you ſhould ſtand in relation to us, as nurſing Fathers, which gives us encouragement to promote our humble requeſts to you, or elſe wee would ſay with the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.4. Look from mee that I may weep bitterly, Labour not to comfort mee, &amp;c. or as <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.2. O that I had in the wilderneſſe a lodging place of a wayfaring man. And thus have wee made known our griefes and deſires to your Worſhips, and leave them upon record with the Lord and with you, knowing that if wee ſhould receive repulſe from you, with the Lord wee ſhall find grace.</p>
               <p>Amongſt others who had ſubſcribed to this writing, <hi>William Aſpinwall</hi> was one, and being returned for one of the Deputies of <hi>Boſton,</hi> it was propounded in the Court, whether hee was fit to bee received a member of the Court, having ſubſcribed to the ſaid writing, which was ſo much to the diſhonour and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt thereof, &amp;c. Whereupon hee was demanded if hee would juſtifie the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contained in the ſaid writing: which when hee had peremptorily affirmed, by the vote of the Court hee was preſently diſmiſſed: Whereupon Mr. <hi>Cogſhall,</hi> another of the Deputies of <hi>Boſton,</hi> who had not ſubſcribed to the ſaid writing, being then a Deputy of the Court, ſpake very boldly to the Court, and told them, that ſeeing they had put out Mr. <hi>Aſpinwall</hi> for that matter, they were beſt make one work of all, for as for himſelfe, though his hand were not to the Petition, yet hee did approve of it, and his hand was to a Proteſtation, which was to the ſame effect; Whereupon the Court diſmiſſed him alſo, and ſent word to <hi>Boſton</hi> to chuſe two new Deputies: then Mr. <hi>Coddington</hi> the third Deputy, moved the Court (by Order from the Town of <hi>Boſton</hi>) that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer cenſure againſt Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> might bee reverſed, and that the Order made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt receiving ſuch as ſhould not bee allowed by the Magiſtrates might bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed; whereby the Court perceived their obſtinate reſolution in maintaining this faction, and thereupon gave Order hee ſhould be ſent for; and for the Law, the anſwer was, that whereas a Declaration had been made of the equity of that Law, and that ſpecially for the ſatisfaction of thoſe of <hi>Boſton,</hi> and an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer had been publiſhed by ſome of them, wherein much reproach and ſlander had been caſt upon the Court, to which a reply had been made above ſix weeks ſince, but was kept in upon expectation that the late Aſſembly would have had ſome good effect, in clearing the points in controverſie, and reconciling the minds of the adverſe party, but they continuing obſtinate and irreconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liable, it was thought fit the whole proceedings about the law ſhould bee brought forth, and accordingly the next day, the Declaration, the Anſwer and the Reply were all brought to the Court, and there openly read; which gave ſuch ſatisfaction to thoſe which were preſent as no man ought to object, and ſome that were of the adverſe party, and had taken offence at the Law, did openly acknowledge themſelves fully ſatisfyed.</p>
               <p>When the Warrant came to the Town of <hi>Boſton,</hi> they aſſembled together and agreed (the greater part of them) to ſend the ſame Deputies which the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:159091:14"/>Court have rejected, pretending that it was their liberty, and thoſe were the ableſt men, &amp;c. but Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> comming amongſt them, and perceiving their raſh and contemptuous hehaviour, by his wiſdome diverted them from that courſe: ſo they choſe two other, but one of them they knew would bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, becauſe his hand was alſo to the ſeditious writing, as it fell out, for hee refuſing to acknowledge his fault in it, was alſo diſmiſſed, and a new War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſent for another to bee choſen, which they never made any return of, but that contempt the Court let paſſe.</p>
               <p>When Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> appeared, it was declared to him, that whereas hee was long ſince convict of ſedition and contempt of authority, and time had been given him from Court to Court, to come to the knowledge of his offence, the Court thought it now time to know how his mind ſtood, whether he would acknowledge his offence, or abide the ſentence of the Court? His Anſwer was to this effect, that hee had committed no ſedition nor contempt, hee had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered nothing but the truth of Chriſt, and for the application of his doctrin it was by others, and not by him, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To which it was anſwered by the Court, that they had not cenſured his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but left it as it was; but his application, by which hee laid the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and the Miniſters, and moſt of the people of God in theſe Churches, under a Covenant of works, and thereupon declared them to bee enemies to Chriſt, and Antichriſts, and ſuch enemies as <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> and the Scribes and Phariſees, &amp;c. perſwading the people to look at them, and deale with them as ſuch, and that hee deſcribed them ſo, as all men might know who hee meant, as well as if hee had named the parties; for hee was preſent in the Court a little before, when both Magiſtrates and Miniſters did openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their judgement in that point, and that they did walk in ſuch a way of evidencing juſtification by ſanctification, &amp;c. as hee held forth to bee a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of works.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the fruits of that Sermon of Mr. <hi>Wheelwright,</hi> together with the Declaration of his judgement in that point both before and ſince, have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it to tend to ſedition: for whereas before hee broached his opinions, there was a peaceable and comely order in all affaires in the Churches, and civill ſtate, &amp;c. now the difference which hee hath raiſed amongſt men, by a falſe diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a Covenant of grace and a Covenant of works; whereby one party is looked at as friends to Chriſt, and the other as his enemies, &amp;c. All things are turned upſide down among us: As firſt, in the Church, hee that will not renounce his ſanctification, and waite for an immediate revelation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, cannot bee admitted, bee hee never ſo godly; hee that is already in the Church, that will not do the ſame, and acknowledge this new light, and ſay as they ſay, is preſently noted, and under-eſteemed, as ſavouring of a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of works: thence it ſpreads into the families, and ſets diviſions between huſband and wife, and other relations there, till the weaker give place to the ſtronger, otherwiſe it turnes to open contention: it is come alſo into Civill and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:159091:14"/>publike affaires, and hath bred great diſturbance there, as appeared in the late expedition againſt the Pequeds; for whereas in former expeditions the Towne of <hi>Boſton</hi> was as forward as any others to ſend of their choyce members, and a greater number then other Townes in the time of the former Governour; now in this laſt ſervice they ſent not a member, but one or two whom they cared not to be rid of, and but a few others, and thoſe of the moſt refuſe ſort, and that in ſuch a careleſſe manner, as gave great diſcouragement to the ſervice, not one man of that ſide accompanying their Paſtour, when he was ſent by the joynt conſent of the Court, and all the Elders upon that expedition, nor ſo much as bidding him farewell; what was the reaſon of this difference? Why, nothing but this, Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> had caught them that the former Governour and ſome of the Magiſtrates then were friends of Chriſt and Free-grace, but the preſent were enemies, &amp;c. Antichriſts, perſecutors: What was the reaſon that the former Governour never ſtirred out, but attended by the Serjeants, with Halberts or Carbines, but this preſent Governour neglected? Why, the people were taught to looke at this, as an enemy to Chriſt, &amp;c. The ſame diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence bath beene obſerved in Towne lots, rates, and in neighbour meetings, and almoſt in all affaires, whereby it is apparent what diſturbance the ſeditious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> hath wrought among us; therefore as the Apoſtle ſaith, I would they were cut off that trouble you; and as <hi>Cain, Hagar,</hi> and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael,</hi> were expelled as troublers of the families, (which were then as common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths) ſo juſtice requires, and the neceſſity of the peace cals for it, that ſuch diſturbers ſhould be put out from among us, ſeeing it is one of their tenents, that it is not poſſible their opinions, and externall peace, can ſtand together; and that the difference betweene them and us is (as they ſay) as wide as between Heaven and Hell.</p>
               <p>Further the Court declared what meanes had beene uſed, to convince him and to reduce him into the right way, as firſt at the Court, when he was convict of his offence, the Miniſters being called together did labour by many ſound arguments, both in publike and private to convince him of his errour and ſinne, but he contemptuouſly ſlighted whatſoever they or the Magiſtrates ſaid to him in that behalfe; and ſince that much paines had beene taken with him, both by conference and writing, not onely privately, but alſo by the late Aſſembly of the Churches, wherein his erroneous opinions, which were the groundworke of his ſeditious Sermon, were clearely confuted, and himſelfe put to ſilence, yet he obſtinately perſiſted in juſtification of his errroneous opinions; and beſides there was an Apologie written in defence of the proceedings of the Court a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, which though it were kept in for a time in expectation of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance, which ſome of his party were in hand with, for juſtification of his Sermon, yet it was long ſince publiſhed, and without queſtion he hath ſeene it: beſides the Court hath uſed much patience towards him from time to time, admoniſhing him of his danger, and waiting for his repentance, in ſtead whereof he hath threatned us with an appeale, and urged us to proceed: To
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:159091:15"/>this Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> replyed, that he would, by the helpe of God, make good his doctrines, and free them from all the arguments which had beene brought againſt them in the late Aſſembly, and denyed that he had ſeene the Apology, but confeſſed that he might have ſeene it if he would. This was obſerved as an argument of the pride of his ſpirit, and wilfull neglect of all the meanes of light in that he would not vouchſafe to read a very briefe writing, and ſuch as ſo much concerned him.</p>
               <p>Although the cauſe was now ready for ſentence, yet night being come, the Court aroſe, and enjoyned him to appeare the next morning.</p>
               <p>The next morning he appeared, but long after the houre appointed; the Court demanded what he had to alleadge, why ſentence ſhould not proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; He anſwered, that there was no ſedition or contempt proved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and whereas he was charged to have ſet forth the Magiſtrates and Miniſters, as enemies to Chriſt, &amp;c. he deſired it might be ſhewed him in what page or leafe of his Sermon he had ſo ſaid of them; The Court anſwered, that he who deſignes a man by ſuch circumſtances, as doe note him out to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intendments, doth as much as if he named the party: when <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of thoſe of the circumciſion, it was as certaine whom he meant as if he named the Jewes; when in <hi>Bobemia</hi> they ſpake of differences betweene men, <hi>ſub una &amp; ſub utraque,</hi> it was all one as to have ſaid Papiſts and Proteſtants; ſo of the Monſtrants and Remonſtrants: for by the meanes of him and his followers, all the people of God in this Countrey were under the diſtinction of men under the Covenant of grace, and men under a Covenant of workes. Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> alleadged a place in <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. where Chriſt ſpeaking againſt the Scribes and Phariſees, no advantage could they take againſt him becauſe he did not name them, but it was anſwered they did not ſpare him for that cauſe, for then they would have taken their advantage at other times; when he did name them. One or two of the Deputies ſpake in his defence, but it was to ſo little purpoſe (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely more out of affection to the party, then true judgement of the ſtate of the cauſe) that the Court had little regard of it. Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded if he had ought elſe to ſpeake, ſaid that there was a double Phariſee in the charge laid upon them. 1. In that the troubles of the Civill State were imputed to him, but as it was by accident, as it is uſuall in preaching of the Goſpel. 2. That it was not his Sermon that was the cauſe of them, but the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. To which the Court anſwered, that it was apparent he was the inſtrument of our troubles, he muſt prove them to be by ſuch accident, and till then the blame muſt reſt upon himſelfe, for we know Chriſt would not owne them, being out of his way. After theſe and many other ſpeeches had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the Court declaring him guilty for troubling the civill peace, both for his ſeditious Sermon, and for his corrupt and dangerous opinions, and for his contemptuous behaviour in divers Courts formerly, and now obſtinately main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining and juſtifying his ſaid errours and offences, and for that he refuſed to depart voluntarily from us, which the Court had now offered him, and in a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:159091:15"/>manner perſwaded him unto; Seeing it was apparent unto him, from that of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> that we could not continue together without the ruine of the whole, he was ſentenced to be disfranchiſed and baniſhed our juriſdiction, and to be put in ſafe cuſtody, except he ſhould give ſufficient ſecurity to depart before the end of March: Upon this he appealed to the Kings Majeſty, but the Court told him an appeale did not lie in this caſe, for the King having given us an authority by his graunt under his great Seale of <hi>England</hi> to heare and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine all cauſes without any reſervation, we were not to admit of any ſuch appeales for any ſuch ſubordinate ſtate, either in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> or other places; and if an appeale ſhould lie in one caſe, it might be challenged in all, and then there would be no uſe of government amongſt us: neither did an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale lie from any Court in any County or Corporation in <hi>England,</hi> but if a party will remove his cauſe to any of the Kings higher Courts, he muſt bring the Kings Writ for it; neither did he tender any appeale, nor call any witneſſes, nor deſired any Act to be entered of it: then he was demanded if be would give ſecurity for his quiet departure, which he refuſing to doe, he was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the cuſtody of the Marſhall. The next morning he bethought himſelfe better, and offered to give ſecurity, alleadging that he did not conceive the day before that a ſentence of baniſhment was pronounced againſt him, he alſo ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to relinquiſh his appeale, and ſaid he would accept of a ſimple baniſhment; The Court anſwered him, that for his appeale, he might doe as he pleaſed, and for his departure, he ſhould have the liberty the Court had offered him, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided he ſhould not preach in the meane time; but that he would not yeeld un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; ſo in the end the Court gave him leave to goe home, upon his promiſe, that if he were not departed out of his juriſdiction within foureteene dayes, he would render himſelfe at the houſe of Mr. <hi>Stanton,</hi> one of the Magiſtrates, there to abide as a priſoner, till the Court ſhould diſpoſe of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Mr. <hi>Cogſhall.</hi>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>THe next who was called, was Mr. <hi>John Cogſhall,</hi> one of the Deacons of <hi>Boſton,</hi> upon his appearance the Court declared that the cauſe why they had ſent for him, was partly by occaſion of his ſpeeches and behaviour in this Court the other day, and partly for ſome light miſcarriages at other times, and that they did looke at him as one that had a principall hand in all our late diſturbances of our publike peace. The firſt thing we doe charge you with, is your juſtfying a writing called a Remonſtrance or Petition, but indeed a ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Libell, and that when Mr. <hi>Aſp.</hi> was queſtioned by the Court about it, you ſtood up uncalled, and juſtified the ſame, ſaying to this effect, that if the Court meant to diſmiſſe him for that, it was beſt to make but one worke of all, for though your ſelfe had not your hand to the Petition, yet you did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thereof, and your hand was to the Proteſtation, which was to the ſame effect; whereupon you being alſo diſmiſſed, uſed clamorous and unbeſeeming ſpeaches to the Court at your departure, whereby we take you to be of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:159091:16"/>ſame minde with thoſe who made the Petition, and therefore liable to the ſame puniſhment; upon this the Petition was openly read, and liberty was granted to him to anſwer for himſelfe. His firſt anſwer was, that what he then ſpake, he ſpake as a member of the Court: to which it was anſwered againe, that 1. hee was no member of the Court ſtanding upon tryall whether to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed or rejected, at ſuch time as he uttered moſt of thoſe ſpeeches. 2. Admit he were, yet it is no privilege of a member to reproach or affront the whole Court, it is licentiouſneſſe, and not liberty, when a man may ſpeake what he liſt; for he was reminded of ſome words he uttered at his going forth of the Court, to this effect, that we had cenſured the truth of Chriſt, and that it was the greateſt ſtroke that ever was given to Free-grace.</p>
               <p>To which he anſwered, that his words were miſtaken; for he ſaid that he would pray that our eyes might be opened to ſee what we did, for he thought it the greateſt ſtroke that ever was given to <hi>N. E.</hi> for he did beleeve that Maſter <hi>Wheelwright</hi> did hold forth the truth. He was further charged, that at the Court, after the day of elections, he complained of injury, that the Petition which was tendered, was not preſently read before they went to election.</p>
               <p>To which being anſwered; that it was not then ſeaſonable, and againſt the order of that day, but the Court were then ready to heare it, if it were tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; whereupon he turned his backe upon the Court, and uſed menacing ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to this effect. That ſince they could not be heard then, they would take another courſe. To which he anſwered (confeſſing he ſpake over haſtily at that time) that his words were onely theſe, then we muſt doe what God ſhall direct us. He was further charged that he ſhould ſay, that halfe the people that were in Church-covenant in <hi>N.E.</hi> were under a Covenant of workes, this he did not deny, but ſaid he proved it by the parable of the ten Virgins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. After theſe and many other ſpeeches had paſſed betweene the Court and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by which it plainely appeared that he had beene a very buſie inſtrument, in occaſioning of our publike diſturbances, and his juſtifying of Mr. <hi>Wheele-wrights</hi> Sermon; and the Petition or Remonſtrance being ſeditious writings, a motion was made for his baniſhment, but he pretended that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be laid to his charge, but matter of different opinion, and that he knew not one example in Scripture, that a man was baniſhed for his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; it was anſwered, that if he had kept his judgement to himſelfe, ſo as the publike peace had not beene troubled or endangered by it, we ſhould have left him to himſelfe, for we doe not challenge power over mens conſciences, but when ſeditious ſpeeches and practiſes diſcover ſuch a corrupt conſcience, it is our duty to uſe authority to reforme both. But though a great part of the Court did encline to a motion for his baniſhment, yet becauſe his ſpeech and behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our at preſent were more modeſt and ſubmiſſe, then formerly they had beene, and for that he excuſed his former intemperances by his much employment and publike buſineſſes, it was thought fit to deliver him from that temptation; ſo he was onely ſentenced to be disfranchized, with admonition no more to occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:159091:16"/>any diſturbance of the publicke peace, either by ſpeech or otherwiſe, upon paine of baniſhment and further cenſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Mr. <hi>Aſpin,</hi>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>THe next who was called was Mr. <hi>William Aſpin,</hi> to whom the Court ſaid that his caſe was in a manner the ſame with Maſter <hi>Cogſhalls,</hi> his hand was to the Petition, he had juſtified Maſter <hi>Wheelwright</hi> his Sermon, and had condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Court, and therefore what could he ſay, why the Court ſhould not proceede to ſentence? For he had beene preſent and heard what was ſaid to Maſter <hi>Cogſhall,</hi> to have convinced him of his fault, and therefore it would be needleſſe to repeate any thing. To this he anſwered and confeſſed the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that his heart was to it as well as his hand, and that that for which Maſter <hi>Wheelwright</hi> was cenſured was for nothing but the truth of Chriſt, and deſired to know what we could lay to his charge therein. The Court told him that he being a member of this civill Body, and going contrary to his relation and oath, to ſtop the courſe of Juſtice in countenancing ſeditious perſons and practiſes againſt the face of authority, this made him a ſeditious perſon. He anſwered he did but preferre a humble Petition, which he could not doe but he muſt intimate ſome cauſe why, and that <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> in his Petition did imply as much of <hi>Davids</hi> unjuſt ſentence againſt him as was in this Petition. The Court replyed that be was ill adviſed to bring that example for his Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which makes clearely againſt him, for <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> doth not charge <hi>David</hi> with any injuſtice not ſo much as by implication, but excuſeth himſelfe and layeth all the blame upon his ſervant. Then he alledged the Petition of <hi>Eſther</hi> to <hi>Abaſuerus;</hi> but neither would that ſerve his turne, for ſhe petitioned for her life, &amp;c. without charging the King with injuſtice. Hee ſtill fled to this plea, that it is lawfull for Subjects to Petition; the Court anſwered that this was no Petition, but a ſeditious Libell, the miſ-naming of a thing doth not alter the nature of it: beſides they called it in the firſt place a Remonſtrance, which implies that they pretended intereſt, and is in the nature of it a plea, which challengeth a right of a party: beſides they give peremptory Judgement in the cauſe, and that directly oppoſite to the judgement of the Court; the Court declared Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> guilty, they proclaime him innocent, the Court judged his ſpeech to be falſe and ſeditious, they affirmed it to be the truth of Chriſt, and the very words of the holy Ghoſt, which is apparently untrue if not blaſphemous. Further in pretending their moderation, they put arguments in the peoples mindes to invite them to violence, by bringing the example of <hi>Peter</hi> drawing his Sword, wherein they blame not his fact, but his raſhneſſe. And that of the People reſcuing <hi>Jonathan,</hi> which to make the more effectuall, they ſay that it was not ſeditious.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it was great arrogance of any private man thus openly to advance his owne judgement of the Court, therefore it will appeare to their Poſterity as a brand of infamy, upon theſe erroneous opinions, that thoſe who maintained
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:159091:17"/>them were not cenſured for their judgement, but for ſeditious practiſes: He further pleaded, that no Petition can be made in ſuch a caſe, but ſomething may bee miſtaken through miſpriſion as trenching upon authority, the Court anſwered, that if they had onely petitioned the Court to remit his cenſure, or had deſired reſpite for further confiderations, or leave to propound their doubts, there could have beene no danger of being miſtaken. Beſides there was no neede of ſuch haſte in Petitioning, ſeeing the ſentence was not given, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring till the next Court, Maſter <hi>Wheelwright</hi> enjoyned onely to appeare there. The Court then being about to give ſentence, Maſter <hi>Aſpin</hi> deſired the Court to ſhew a rule in Scripture for baniſhment; the Court anſwered as before, that <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Iſmael</hi> were baniſhed for diſturbance: hee replied that if a Father give a child a portion and ſent him forth, it was not baniſhment: but it was anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the Scripture calls it a caſting out, not a ſending forth; and one ſaid further that he was a childe worthy of ſuch a portion.</p>
               <p>Then the ſentence of the Court was for his diſ-franchiſement and baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and time given him to the laſt of <hi>March</hi> upon ſecurity for his departure then, which hee preſently tendered, and ſo was diſmiſſed. The Court inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded onely to have diſ-franchiſed him, as they had done Mr. <hi>Cogſhall,</hi> but his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour was ſo contemptuous, and his ſpeeches ſo peremptory, that occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a further aggravation, and it appeared afterward to bee by an over-ruling hand of God, for the next day it was diſcovered, that hee was the man that did frame the Petition, and drew many to ſubſcribe to it, and ſome had their names put to it without their knowledge, and in his firſt draught there was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſages ſo foule, as hee was forced to put them out, and yet many had not ſubſcribed, but upon his promiſe that it ſhould not bee delivered without advice of Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> which was never done.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>William Baulſton, Ed. Hutchiſon.</label>
               </p>
               <p>AFter theſe, two of the Serjeants of <hi>Boſton</hi> were called, <hi>William Baulſton, &amp; Ed. Hutchiſon,</hi> theſe both had their hands to the Petition, and juſtifyed the ſame, <hi>William Baulſton</hi> told the Court, that hee knew that if ſuch a petition had been made in any other place in the world, there would have been no fault found with it. The other told the Court, (turning himſelfe in a ſcornfull manner) that if they took away his eſtate, they muſt keep his wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; for which hee was preſently committed to the Officer. The Court rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned a good while with them both, but they were peremptory, and would acknowledge no failing, and becauſe of their contemptuous ſpeeches, and for that they were known to bee very buſie perſons, and ſuch as had offered contempt to the Magiſtrates, for that they were not of their opinion, they were diſ-franchiſed and ſined, <hi>William Baulſton</hi> twenty pounds, <hi>Ed. Hutchiſon</hi> foety pounds.</p>
               <p>The next morning <hi>Ed. Hutchiſon</hi> acknowledged his fault in his miſ-beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in the face of the Court, and ſo was releaſed of his impriſonment, but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:159091:17"/>both were diſabled from bearing any publick Office.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Tho. Marſhal, Dynely, Dier, Rich. Gridly.</label>
               </p>
               <p>ANother day were called foure more of the principall ſtirring men, who had ſubſcribed to the Petition, <hi>Thomas Marſhal</hi> the Ferry-man, who ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyed the Petition ſo farre, that hee would not acknowledge any fault; yet hee anſwered more modeſtly then the former, therefore hee was not fined, but diſ-franchiſed, and put out of his place. <hi>Dynely,</hi> and <hi>Dier,</hi> had little to ſay for themſelves, but perfiſting in their juſtification, they were alſo diſ-franchiſed: likewiſe <hi>Rich. Gridly,</hi> an honeſt poore man, but very apt to meddle in publick affaires, beyond his calling or skill, (which indeed was the fault of them all, and of many others in the Country) meane condition, and weake parts, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing to ſay, but that he could find no fault, &amp;c. was diſ-franchiſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Miſtris Hutchiſon.</label>
               </p>
               <p>ALl theſe (except Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi>) were but young branches, ſprung out of an old root, the Court had now to do with the head of all this faction, <hi>(Dux faemina facti)</hi> a woman had been the breeder and nouriſher of all theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, one Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon,</hi> the wife of Mr. <hi>William Hutchiſon</hi> of <hi>Boſton</hi> (a very honeſt and peaceable man of good eſtate) and the daughter of Mr. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> ſometimes a Preacher in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> after of <hi>London,</hi> a woman of a haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and fierce carriage, of a nimble wit and active ſpirit, and a very voluble tongue, more bold then a man, though in underſtanding and judgement, infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to many women. This woman had learned her skil in <hi>England,</hi> and had diſcovered ſome of her opinions in the Ship, as ſhee came over, which had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſome jealouſie of her, which gave occaſion of ſome delay of her admiſſion, when ſhee firſt deſired fellowſhip with the Church of <hi>Boſton,</hi> but ſhee cunningly diſſembled and coloured her opinions, as ſhee ſoon got over that block, and was admitted into the Church, then ſhee began to go to work, and being a woman very helpfull in the times of child-birth, and other occaſions of bodily infirmities, and well furniſhed with means for thoſe purpoſes, ſhee eaſily inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated her ſelfe into the affections of many, and the rather, becauſe ſhee was much inquiſitive of them about their ſpiritual eſtates, and in diſcovering to them the danger they were in, by truſting to common gifts and graces, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch witneſſe of the Spirit, as the Scripture holds out for a full evidence; whereby many were convinced that they had gone on in a Covenant of works, and were much humbled thereby, and brought to inquire more after the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, without whom all their gifts and graces, all their contributions, &amp;c. would prove but legall, and would vaniſh: all this was well, and ſuited with the publick Miniſtery, which went along in the ſame way, and all the faithful imbraced it, and bleſſed God for the good ſucceſſe that appeared from this diſcovery. But when ſhee had thus prepared the way by ſuch wholeſome truths, then ſhee begins to ſet forth her own ſtuffe, and taught that no ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:159091:18"/>was any evidence of a good eſtate, except their juſtification were firſt cleared up to them by the immediate witneſſe of the Spirit, and that to ſee any work of grace, (either faith or repentance, &amp;c.) before this immediate witneſſe, was a Covenant of works: whereupon many good ſoules, that had been of long approved godlineſſe, were brought to renounce all the work of grace in them, and to wait for this immediate revelation: then ſprung up alſo that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the in-dwelling of the perſon of the Holy Ghoſt, and of union with Chriſt, and Juſtification before faith, and a denying of any gifts or graces, or inherent qualifications, and that Chriſt was all, did all, and that the ſoule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained alwayes as a dead Organ: and other of thoſe groſſe errours, which were condemned in the late Aſſembly, and whereof diverſe had been quaſhed, by the publick Miniſtery; but the maine and bottom of all, which tended to quench all indevour, and to bring to a dependance upon an immediate witneſſe of the Spirit, without ſight of any gift or grace, this ſtuck faſt, and prevailed ſo, as it began to bee oppoſed, and ſhee being queſtioned by ſome, who mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled that ſuch opinions ſhould ſpread ſo faſt, ſhee made anſwer, that where ever ſhee came they muſt and they ſhould ſpread, and indeed it was a wonder upon what a ſudden the whole Church of <hi>Boſton</hi> (ſome few excepted) were become her new converts, and infected with her opinions, and many alſo out of the Church, and of other Churches alſo, yea, many prophane perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of her opinion, for it was a very eaſie, and acceptable way to heaven, to ſee nothing, to have nothing, but waite for Chriſt to do all; ſo that after ſhee had thus prevailed, and had drawn ſome of eminent place and parts to her party (whereof ſome profited ſo well, as in a few moneths they outwent their teacher) then ſhee kept open houſe for all commers, and ſet up two Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture dayes in the week, when they uſually met at her houſe, threeſcore or foureſcore perſons, the pretence was to repeate Sermons, but when that was done, ſhee would comment upon the Doctrines, and interpret all paſſages at her pleaſure, and expound dark places of Scripture, ſo as whatſoever the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter held forth (for this was one of her tenents, that the whole Scripture in the Letter of it held forth nothing but a Covenant of works) ſhee would bee ſure to make it ſerve her turn for the confirming of her maine principles, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this was another, That the darker our ſanctification is, the cleerer is our juſtification; And indeed moſt of her new tenents tended to ſlothfulneſſe, and quench all indevour in the creature: and now was there no ſpeech ſo much in uſe, as of vilifying ſanctification, and all for advancing Chriſt and free grace, and the whole pedegree of the Covenant of works was ſet forth with all its Complements, beginning at <hi>Cain,</hi> If thou doſt well ſhalt thou not bee accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? then it is explained and ratifyed at Mount <hi>Sinui,</hi> and delivered in the two Tables, and after ſprinkled with the blood of Chriſt, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24. and ſo carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on in the Letter of the Scripture, till it bee compleat, as the Covenant of Grace by the Spirit, ſeales, forgiveneſſe of ſins, one of the venters whereon Chriſt begets children, &amp;c. and in the end wherefore is all this adoe, but that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:159091:18"/>having a more cleanly way, to lay all that oppoſed her, (being neere all the Elders and moſt of the faithfull Chriſtians in this Countrey) under a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of workes, ſhee might with the more credit, diſcloſe and advance her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-piece of immediate revelations, under the faire pretence of the Covenant of free Grace; wherein ſhee had not failed of her ayme, to the utter ſubverſion both of Churches and civill ſtate, if the moſt wiſe and mercifull providence of the Lord had not prevented it by keeping ſo many of the Magiſtrates, and Elders, free from the infection: for upon the countenance which it took from ſome eminent perſons, her opinions began to hold up their heads, in Church Aſſemblies, and in the Court of Juſtice, ſo as it was held a matter of offence to ſpeak any thing againſt them in either Aſſembly: thence ſprang all that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Paſtour of <hi>Boſton,</hi> for his free and faithfull ſpeech in the Court, though required and approved: thence took Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> courage to inveigh in his ſermon againſt men in a Covenant of works (as hee placed them) and to proclaim them all enemies to Chriſt, Scribes and Phariſees, &amp;c. whereas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee was wont to teach in a plaine and gentle ſtile, and though hee would ſometimes glaunce upon theſe opinions, yet it was modeſtly and reſervedly, not in ſuch a peremptory and cenſorious manner, as hee did then and after; for they made full account the day had been theirs, But bleſſed bee the Lord, the ſnare is broken, and wee are delivered, and this woman who was the root of all theſe troubles, ſtands now before the ſeat of Juſtice, to bee rooted out of her ſtation, by the hand of authority, guided by the finger of divine providence, as the ſequell will ſhow.</p>
               <stage>When ſhee appeared, the Court ſpake to her to this effect.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon.</hi> You are called hither as one of thoſe who have had a great ſhare in the cauſes of our publick diſturbances, partly by thoſe erroneous opinions which you have broached and divulged amongſt us, and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, partly by countenancing and incouraging ſuch as have ſowed ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions amongſt us, partly by caſting reproach upon the fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>full Miniſters of this Countrey, and upon their Miniſtery, and ſo weakning their hands in the work of the Lord, and raiſing prejudice againſt them, in the hearts of their people, and partly by maintaining weekly and publick meetings in your houſe, to the offence of all the Countrey, and the detriment of many families, and ſtill upholding the ſame, ſince ſuch meetings were clearely condemned in the late generall Aſſembly.</p>
                  <p>Now the end of your ſending for, is, that either upon ſight of your errors, and other offences, you may bee brought to acknowledge, and reforme the ſame, or otherwiſe that wee may take ſuch courſe with you as you may trouble us no further.</p>
                  <p>Wee do deſire therefore to know of you, whether you will Juſtifie and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine what is laid to your charge or not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I am called here to anſwer to ſuch things as are laid to my charge, name one of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:159091:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:159091:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:159091:20"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>Have you countenanced, or will you juſtifie thoſe ſeditious practiſes which have been cenſured here in this Court?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you ask mee upon point of conſcience?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>No, your conſcience you may keep to your ſelf, but if in this cauſe you ſhall countenance and incourage thoſe that thus tranſgreſſe the Law, you muſt bee called in queſtion for it, and that is not for your conſcience, but for your practiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>What Law have they tranſgreſſed? the Law of God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, the fifth Commandement, which commands us to honour Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, which includes all in authority, but theſe ſeditious practiſes of theirs, have caſt reproach and diſhonour upon the Fathers of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>Do I intertaine, or maintaine them in their actions, wherein they ſtand againſt any thing that God hath appointed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, you have juſtified Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> his Sermon, for which you know hee was convict of ſedition, and you have likewiſe countenanced and encouraged thoſe that had their hands to the Petition.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>I deny it, I am to obey you only in the Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>You cannot deny but you had your hand in the Petition.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>Put caſe, I do feare the Lord, and my Parent doe not, may not I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain one that feares the Lord, becauſe my Father will not let mee? I may put honour upon him as a childe of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>That's nothing to the purpoſe, but wee cannot ſtand to diſpute cauſes with you now, what ſay you to your weekly publick meetings? can you ſhew a warrant for them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>I will ſhew you how I took it up, there were ſuch meetings in uſe before I came, and becauſe I went to none of them, this was the ſpeciall reaſon of my taking up this courſe, wee began it but with five or ſix, and though it grew to more in future time, yet being tolerated at the firſt, I knew not why it might not continue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>There were private meetings indeed, and are ſtill in many places, of ſome few neighbours, but not ſo publick and frequent as yours, and are of uſe for increaſe of love, and mutuall edification, but yours are of another na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if they had been ſuch as yours they had been evill, and therfore no good warrant to juſtifie yours; but anſwer by what authority, or rule, you uphold them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>By <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. where the elder women are to teach the younger.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>So wee allow you to do, as the Apoſtle there meanes, privately, and upon occaſion, but that gives no warrant of ſuch ſet meetings for that purpoſe; and beſides, you take upon you to teach many that are elder then your ſelfe, neither do you teach them that which the Apoſtle commands, <hi>viz.</hi> to keep at home.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you pleaſe to give mee a rule againſt is, and I will yeeld?</p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:159091:20"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>You muſt have a rule for it, or elſe you cannot do it in faith, yet you have a plaine rule againſt it; I permit not a woman to teach.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>That is meant of teaching men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>If a man in diſtreſſe of conſcience or other temptation, &amp;c. ſhould come and ask your counſell in private, might you not teach him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>Then it is cleare, that it is not meant of teaching men, but of teaching in publick.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>It is ſaid, I will poure my Spirit upon your Daughters, and they ſhall propheſie, &amp;c. If God give mee a gift of Prophecy, I may uſe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt, the Apoſtle applies that prophecy unto thoſe extraordinary times, and the gifts of miracles and tongues were common to many as well as the gift of Prophecy. Secondly, in teaching your children, you exerciſe your gift of prophecy, and that within your calling.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>I teach not in a publick congregation: The men of <hi>Berea</hi> are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for examining <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine; wee do no more but read the notes of our teachers Sermons, and then reaſon of them by ſearching the Scriptures.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court.</speaker>
                  <p>You are gone from the nature of your meeting, to the kind of exerciſe, wee will follow you in this, and ſhew you your offence in them, for you do not as the <hi>Bereans</hi> ſearch the Scriptures for their confirming in the truths delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but you open your teachers points, and declare his meaning, and correct wherein you think he hath failed, &amp;c. and by this meanes you abaſe the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and authority of the publick Miniſtery, and advance your own gifts, as if hee could not deliver his matter ſo clearely to the hearers capacity as your ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>Prove that, that any body doth that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, you are the woman of moſt note, and of beſt abilities, and if ſome other take upon them the like, it is by your teaching and example, but you ſhew not in all this, by what authority you take upon you to bee ſuch a publick inſtructer: (after ſhee had ſtood a ſhort time, the Court gave her leave to ſit downe, for her countenance diſcovered ſome bodily infirmity.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>Here is my authority, <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> tooke upon them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct <hi>Apollo,</hi> more perfectly, yet he was a man of good parts, but they being better inſtructed might teach him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>See how your argument ſtands, <hi>Priſcilla</hi> with her husband, tooke <hi>Apollo</hi> home to inſtruct him privately, therefore Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon</hi> without her husband may teach ſixty or eighty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>I call them not, but if they come to me, I may inſtruct them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>Yet you ſhew us not a rule.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>I have given you two places of Scripture.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>But neither of them will ſute your practiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>Muſt I ſhew my name written therein?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court</speaker>
                  <p>You muſt ſhew that which muſt be aequivalent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>ing your Miniſtry
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:159091:21"/>is publicke, you would have them receive your inſtruction, as comming from ſuch an Ordinance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hutch.</speaker>
                  <p>They muſt not take it as it comes from me, but as it comes from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and if I tooke upon me a publick Miniſtery, I ſhould breake a rule, but not in exerciſing a gift of Prophecy, and I would ſee a rule to turne away them that come to me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Court,</speaker>
                  <p>It is your exerciſe which drawes them, and by occaſion thereof, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny families are neglected, and much time loſt, and a great damage comes to the Common-wealth thereby, which wee that are betruſted with, as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Common-wealth, are not to ſuffer.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>Divers other ſpeeches paſſed to and fro about this matter, the iſſue was, that not being able to bring any rule to juſtifie this her diſordered courſe, ſhe ſaid ſhe walked by the rule of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> which ſhe called the rule of the new creature, but what rule that was, ſhe would not, or ſhe could not tell, neither would ſhe conſent to lay downe her meetings, except authority did put them downe, and then ſhe might be ſubject to authority.</p>
               <p>Then the Court laid to her charge, the reproach ſhe had caſt upon the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and Miniſtery in this Country, ſaying that none of them did preach the Covenant of free Grace, but Maſter <hi>Cotton,</hi> and that they have not the Seale of the Spirit, and ſo were not able Miniſters of the New Teſtament: ſhe denyed the words, but they were affirmed by divers of the Miniſters, being deſired by the Court to be preſent for that end. The matter was thus, It being reported abroad that Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon</hi> did ſlight them and their Miniſtery in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon talke, as if they did preach nothing but a Covenant of workerr, becauſe they preſſed much for faith and love, &amp;c. without holding forth ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate witneſſe of the Spirit as ſhe pretended, they adviſed with Maſter <hi>Cotton</hi> about it, and a meeting was appointed at his houſe, and ſhe being ſent for, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the reaſon why ſhe had uſed ſuch ſpeeches, at firſt ſhe would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them, but being told that they could prove them by witneſſes, and perſwaded to deale freely and truly therein, ſhe ſaid that the feare of man was a ſnare, and therefore ſhe was glad ſhe had this opportunity to open her minde, and thereupon ſhe told them, that there was a wide difference betweene Maſter <hi>Cottons</hi> Miniſtery and theirs, and that they could not hold forth a Covenant of free Grace, becauſe they had not the Seale of the Spirit, and that they were not able Miniſters of the New Teſtament.</p>
               <p>It was neare night, ſo the Court brake up, and ſhe was enjoyned to appeare againe the next morning. When ſhe appeared the next day, ſhe objected that the Miniſters had ſpoken in their owne cauſe, and that they ought not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers and witneſſes both, and required that they might be ſworne to what they had ſpoken: to which the Court anſwered, that if it were needfull, an oath ſhould be given them: but becauſe the whole Court (in a manner man by man) did declare themſelves to be fully ſatisfied of the truth of their teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, they being 6. or 7. men of long approved godlineſſe, and ſincerity in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:159091:21"/>their courſe, and for that it was alſo generally obſerved, that thoſe of her par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty did looke at their miniſtery (for the moſt part) as a way of the Covenant of workes, and one had beene puniſhed about halfe a yeere before, for report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the like of them. The Court did pauſe a while at it, whereupon ſhe ſaid that ſhe had Mr. <hi>Wilſons</hi> notes of that conference, which were otherwiſe then they had related: the Court willed her to ſhew them, but her anſwer was ſhee had left them at home: whereupon Mr. <hi>Wilſon</hi> (with the leave of the Court) ſaid, that if ſhe brought forth his notes, they ſhould finde written at the foote of them, that he had not wirtten downe all that was ſpoken, but being often interrupted, he had omitted divers paſſages; then ſhe appealed to Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> who being called, and deſired to declare what he remembred of her ſpeeches, ſaid, that he remembred onely that which tooke impreſſion on him, for he was much grieved that ſhe ſhould make ſuch compariſon betweene him and his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, but yet he tooke her meaning to be onely of a graduall difference, when ſhe ſaid that they did not hold forth a Covenant of Free-grace, as he did, for ſhe likened them to Chriſts Diſciples, and their miniſtery, before his aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and before the holy Ghoſt was come downe upon them; and when ſhe was asked by ſome of them, why they could not preach a Covenant of Free-grace, ſhe made anſwer, becauſe they had not the Seale of the Spirit: upon this the Court wiſhed her to conſider, that Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> did in a manner agree with the teſtimony of the reſt of the Elders: and as he rembembred onely ſo much as at preſent tooke moſt impreſſion in him, ſo the reſt of the Elders had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to remember ſome other paſſages, which he might not heare, or not ſo much obſerve as they whom it ſo neerely and properly concerned; All this would not ſatisfie Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon,</hi> but ſhe ſtill called to have them ſworne, whereupon the Court being weary of the clamour, and that all mouths might be ſtopped, required three of the Miniſters to take an oath, and thereupon they confirmed their former teſtimony.</p>
               <p>Upon this ſhe began to ſpeake her mind, and to tell of the manner of Gods dealing with her, and how he revealed himſelfe to her, and made her know what ſhe had to doe; The Governour perceiving whereabout ſhe went, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted her, and would have kept her to the matter in hand, but ſeeing her very unwilling to be taken off, he permitted her to proceed. Her ſpeech was to this effect.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>When I was in old <hi>England,</hi> I was much troubled at the conſtitution of the Churches there, ſo farre, as I was ready to have joyned to the Separation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I ſet apart a day for humiliation by my ſelfe, to ſeeke direction from God, and then did God diſcover unto me the unfaithfulneſſe of the Churches, and the danger of them, and that none of thoſe Miniſters could preach the Lord Jeſus aright, for he had brought to my mind, that in the 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.3. Every ſpirit that confeſſeth not, that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is the ſpirit of Antichriſt; I marvelled what this ſhould meane, for I knew that neither Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:159091:22"/>nor Papiſts did deny that Chriſt was come in the fleſh; and are the Turkes then the onely Antichriſts? now I had none to open the Scripture to me, but the Lord, he muſt be the Prophet, then he brought to my mind ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scripture, He that denies the Teſtament, denies the death of the Teſtator, from whence the Lord did let me ſee, that every one that did not preach the New Covenant, denies the death of the Teſtator; then it was revealed to me that the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> were theſe Antichriſts, but I knew not how to beare this, I did in my heart riſe up againſt it, then I begged of the Lord that this Atheiſme might not be in my heart: after I had begged this light, a twelve moneth together, at laſt he let me ſee how I did oppoſe Chriſt Jeſus, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to mee that place in <hi>Eſay</hi> 46.12, 13. and from thence ſhewed me the Atheiſme of my owne heart, and how I did turne in upon a Covenant of works, and did oppoſe Chriſt Jeſus; from which time the Lord did diſcover to me all ſorts of Miniſters, and how they taught, and to know what voyce I heard, which was the voyce of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and which of Chriſt; the voyce of my beloved, from the voyce of ſtrangers; and thenceforth I was the more carefull whom I heard, for after our teacher Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> and my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Wheelwright</hi> were put downe, there was none in <hi>England</hi> that I durſt heare. Then it pleaſed God to reveale himſelfe to me in that of <hi>Eſay</hi> 30.20. Though the Lord give thee the bread of adverſity, &amp;c. yet thine eyes ſhall ſee thy teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; after this the Lord carrying Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> to <hi>New England</hi> (at which I was much troubled) it was revealed to me, that I muſt go thither alſo, and that there I ſhould be perſecuted and ſuffer much trouble. I will give you another Scripture, <hi>Jer.</hi> 46. Feare not <hi>Jacob</hi> my ſervant, for I am with thee, I will make a full end of all the Nations, &amp;c. then the Lord did reveale himſelfe to me, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon a Throne of Juſtice, and all the world appearing before him, and though I muſt come to <hi>New England,</hi> yet I muſt not feare nor be diſmaied. The Lord brought another Scripture to me, <hi>Eſay</hi> 8.9. The Lord ſpake this to me with a ſtrong hand, and inſtructed me that I ſhould not walke in the way of this people, &amp;c. I wil give you one place more which the Lord brought to me by immediate revelations, and that doth concerne you all, it is in <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. When the Preſidents and Princes could find nothing againſt him, becauſe he was faithfull, they ſought matter againſt him concerning the Law of his God, to caſt him into the Lions denne; ſo it was revealed to me that they ſhould plot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, but the Lord bid me not to feare, for he that delivered <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the three children, his hand was not ſhortened. And ſee this Scripture fulfilled this day in mine eyes, therefore take heed what yee goe about to doe unto me, for you have no power over my body, neither can you do me any harme, for I am in the hands of the eternall Jehovah my Saviour, I am at his appointment, the bounds of my habitation are caſt in Heaven, no further doe I eſteeme of any mortall man, then creatures in his hand, I feare none but the great Jehovah, which hath foretold me of theſe things, and I doe verily beleeve that he will deliver me out of our hands, therefore take heed how you proceed againſt me;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:159091:22"/>for I know that for this you goe about to doe to me, God will ruine you and your poſterity, and this whole State.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>When ſhe had thus vented her mind, the Court demanded of her, how ſhe expected to be delivered, whether by miracle as <hi>Daniel</hi> was, to which ſhe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, yes, by miracle as <hi>Daniel</hi> was. Being further demanded how ſhee did know that it was God that did reveale theſe things to her, and not Satan? She anſwered, how did <hi>Abraham</hi> know that it was the voyce of God, when he commanded him to ſacrifice his ſonne?</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> being preſent, and deſired by the Court to deliver his judgement about Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon</hi> her Revelations, anſwered, there be two ſorts of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, ſome are without or beſides Scripture, thoſe I looke at as Satanicall, and tending to much danger, other are ſuch as the Apoſtle ſpeakes of, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. where he praieth for a ſpirit of revelation to be given them, thoſe are never diſpenſed but according to the word of God, though the word revelation be uncouth, yet in Scripture ſenſe I thinke it not lawfull ſo to expreſſe it, and when ever it comes, it comes with the miniſtery of the word. Being againe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to expreſſe himſelfe particularly concerning her revelations, he deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of her (by the leave of the Court) whether by a miracle ſhe doth meane a worke beyond the power of nature, or onely above common providence? for if (as you ſay) you expect deliverance from this Court beyond the power of nature, then I ſhould ſuſpect ſuch a revelation to be falſe. To this ſhe anſwered, you know when it comes, God doth not deſcribe the way. Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> asked her againe, whether (when ſhee ſaid ſhee ſhould be delivered) ſhe meant a delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from the ſentence of the Court, or from the calamity of it? She anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yes, from the calamity of it. Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon</hi> having thus freely and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered her ſelfe, the Court and all the reſt of the Aſſembly (except thoſe of her owne party) did obſerve a ſpeciall providence of God, that (while ſhee went about to cover ſuch offences as were laid to her charge, by putting mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters upon proofe, and then quarrelling with the evidence) her owne mouth ſhould deliver her into the power of the Court, as guilty of that which all ſuſpected her for, but were not furniſhed with proofe ſufficient to proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her, for here ſhe hath manifeſted, that her opinions and practiſe have been the cauſe of al our diſturbances, &amp; that ſhe walked by ſuch a rule as cannot ſtand with the peace of any State; for ſuch bottomleſſe revelations, as either came without any word, or without the ſenſe of the word, (which was framed to humane capacity) if they be allowed in one thing, muſt be admitted a rule in all things; for they being above reaſon and Scripture, they are not ſubject to controll: Againe, ſhe hath given a reaſon why ſhe hath ſo much ſlighted the faithfull Miniſters of Chriſt here, why? it was revealed to her long ſince in <hi>England,</hi> that all the packe of them were Antichriſtians, ſo as ſhe durſt heare none of them, after Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> and Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> were once gone; for they could not preach Chriſt and the new Covenant (as ſhe affirmes), why, but they did preach ſomewhat, and if they could not hold forth Chriſt in a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:159091:23"/>Covenant of Free-grace, then muſt they needs hold him forth in a Covenant of workes, then are they not able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, nor ſealed by the Spirit; for the ſervants of God, who are come over into <hi>New England,</hi> do not thinke themſelves more ſpirituall then other of their brethren whom they have left behind, nor that they can or doe hold forth the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in their miniſtery, more truly then he was held forth in <hi>England,</hi> and ſeeing their miniſtery was a moſt precious ſweete ſavour to all the Saints before ſhe came hither, it is eaſie to diſcerne from what ſinke that ill vapour hath riſen, which hath made ſo many of her ſeduced party to loath now the ſmell of thoſe flowers which they were wont to find ſweetneſſe in: yet this is not all (though it be too too vile) ſhe can fetch a revelation that ſhall reach the Magiſtrates and the whole Court, and the ſucceeding generations, and ſhe hath Scripture for it alſo, <hi>Daniel</hi> muſt be a type of Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon,</hi> the Lions denne of the Court of juſtice, and the Preſidents and Princes of the reverend Elders here, and all muſt ſort to this concluſion, ſhe muſt be delivered by miracle, and all we muſt be ruined; See the impudent boldneſſe of a proud dame, that <hi>Athaliah</hi>-like makes havocke of all that ſtand in the way of her ambitious ſpirit; ſhe had boaſted before that her opinions muſt prevaile, neither could ſhe endure a ſtop in her way, as appeared once upon a ſlight occaſion when her reputation being a little touch'd upon a miſtake, yet ſo carried as ſhe could not get the party upon that advantage which ſhe expected, ſhe vented her impatience with ſo fierce ſpeech and countenance, as one would hardly have gueſſed her to have been an Antitype of <hi>Daniel,</hi> but rather of the Lions after they were let looſe. The like appeared in her, when ſhe could not have her will againſt her faithfull Paſtor for his oppoſing her opinions, as ſhe apprehended, ſo as neither reaſon, nor Scripture, nor the judgement and example of ſuch as ſhe reverenced could ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe her diſpleaſure. So that the Court did clearely diſcerne, where the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine was of all our diſtempers, and the Tragedy of <hi>Munſter</hi> (to ſuch as had read it) gave juſt occaſion to feare the danger we were in, ſeeing (by the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Luther</hi> writing of thoſe troublous times) we had not to doe with ſo ſimple a Devill, as managed that buſineſſe, and therefore he had the leſſe feare of him; but Satan ſeemed to have commiſſion now to uſe his utmoſt cunning to undermine the Kingdome of Chriſt here (as the ſame <hi>Luther</hi> foretold, he would doe, when he ſhould enterprize any ſuch innovation under the cleare light of the Goſpel) ſo as the like hath not beene knowne in former ages, that ever ſo many wiſe, ſober, and well grounded Chriſtians, ſhould ſo ſuddenly be ſeduced by the meanes of a woman, to ſticke ſo faſt to her, even in ſome things wherein the whole current of Scripture goeth againſt them, and that notwithſtanding that her opinions and practiſe have beene ſo groſſe in ſome particulars, as their knowledge and ſincerity would not ſuffer them to approve, yet ſuch intereſt hath ſhe gotten in their hearts, as they ſeeke cloakes to cover the nakedneſſe of ſuch deformities, as in the meane time they are aſhamed to behold.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:159091:23"/>
               </p>
               <p>The Court ſaw now an inevitable neceſſary to rid her away, except wee would bee guilty, not only of our own ruine, but alſo of the Goſpel, ſo in the end the ſentence of baniſhment was pronounced againſt her, and ſhee was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Marſhall, till the Court ſhould diſpoſe of her.</p>
               <p>Another day, Captaine <hi>John <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderhill</hi> was ſent for, and being charged with joyning in the ſaid Petition, acknowledged the ſame, profeſſing that hee could ſee no fault in it: being demanded a rule by which hee might take ſo much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, as publickly to contradict the ſentence of the Court, &amp;c. hee alledged the example of <hi>Joab</hi> his rough ſpeech to <hi>David,</hi> when hee retired himſelf for <hi>Abſaloms</hi> death, and that <hi>David</hi> did not reprove him for it. To this the Court anſwered.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That <hi>Joab</hi> was then in the matters of his own calling, and being Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the Army, had liberty by his place to give advice to the King in cauſes of that nature, but when hee failed in the manner of his ſpeech, therein hee is not to bee excuſed, and therefore not to bee followed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Joab</hi> did not contradict or reprove any Judiciall ſentence of the King, but only an inordinate paſſion.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Hee was occaſioned by an urgent neceſſity of the ſafety of the King and State.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, That which hee ſpake was in private, for the King had withdrawn himſelf.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, It appeares that <hi>David</hi> did take it as a great miſcarriage, for hee preſently diſplaced him.</p>
               <p>Againe, in our cauſe the Captain was but a private man, and had no calling to deale in the affaires of the Court, therefore no warrant from hence. Hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted much upon the liberty which all States do allow to <hi>Military</hi> Officers, for free ſpeech, &amp;c. and that himſelf had ſpoken ſometimes as freely to Count <hi>Naſſaw.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it was anſwered, wee are not to look at whatſome do tolerate, but what is lawfull, and there may bee a reaſon of State, to connive at that diſorder at ſome ſeaſon, which may not with honour and ſafety bee permitted at another.</p>
               <p>Being further demanded, how they came ſo many of them, to bee ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly agreed in ſo weighty and doubtfull a caſe, hee anſwered, that many of them being preſent when Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> was convict of ſedition, they were ſore grieved at it, and ſuddenly ruſhing out of the Court, a ſtrange motion came into all their mindes, ſo as they ſaid (in a manner all together) Come let us petition; and for his part, from that time to this, his conſcience which then led him to it, will not ſuffer him to retract it.</p>
               <p>The Court pityed him much, and were grieved at his obſtinacy, that when all his arguments were taken away, hee had no defence left, hee would yet main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a bad cauſe by the light of a deluded conſcience, and withall they tooke notice how theſe ungrounded revelations began to work, and what dangerous conſequences were like to follow of them, when ſo many perſons upon ſuch a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:159091:24"/>ſudden motion had no ſcruple to enterprize ſuch a ſeditious action, nor can bee brought by any light of reaſon or Scripture, to ſee their error: ſo the Court (when they ſaw no other remedy) diſ-franchiſed him, and diſcharged him of his place, but allowed him his quarters means.</p>
               <p>There were diverſe who were not preſent when that ſudden motion or reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation firſt ſet the Petition on foot, but were drawn in after, who ſoon found their error, and did as freely acknowledge it, and deſired to have their names put out of it, which was eaſily granted, and their offence with a loving ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition remitted.</p>
               <p>It had been obſerved a good time ſince, that ſome of the leaders of this facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (by occaſion of new Diſciples, being inquiſitive about their tenents) would let fall theſe anſwers, I have many things to tell you, but you cannot beare them now; and there is a great light to break forth, if men do not reſiſt it, and you ſhall ſee the bottom hereafter; and one of them reproved the reſt, telling them that they had ſpoyled their cauſe, by being over haſty and too open, &amp;c. And now it began to appeare, what their meanings were, for after Miſtris <hi>Hut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſon</hi> had diſcovered the ſecret by her ſpeech in the Court, then others open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their minds, and profeſſedly maintained theſe Enthuſiaſmes as the Oracles of God. And that ſuch revelations as <hi>Abraham</hi> had to kill his Son, and as <hi>Paul</hi> had in the Ship, and when hee was caught up into the third heaven, &amp;c. were ordinary, ſo that Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> took notice of the danger of them, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly confuted them in diverſe Sermons. Among other like paſſages there was one that fell out, at Mr. <hi>Wheel</hi> his farewell to thoſe whom hee uſed to Preach unto at the Mount.</p>
               <p>One of his own Scholars told him openly, that hee had Preached Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſme, and had ſet up a Chriſt againſt a Chriſt; the ſame party main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained immediate revelations without any word at all, ſaying, that the free promiſes were only for thoſe under the Law, but wee are to look for all our aſſurance by immediate Revelation, and that in the New Teſtament there are no ſignes, no not our baptiſme, for the baptiſme of water is of no uſe to us, when once wee are baptized with the Holy Ghoſt: hee ſaid alſo that a man might bee adopted and not juſtified, and that every new creature is as a dead lump, not acting at all, but as Chriſt acts in him, and denyed all inherent righteouſneſſe, and that the commandements were a dead Letter. Theſe things were ſo groſſe, as Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> could not but contradict him, yet hee did it ſo tenderly, as might well diſcover his neere agreement in the points, though his wiſdome ſerved him to bee more reſerved till a fitter ſeaſon; for that poore man being newly come on to the profeſſion of Religion, muſt needs learn thoſe points of Mr. <hi>Wheel,</hi> or draw them as neceſſary conſequences from ſome of his tenents: And it is frequently found to bee an effect of all unſound and unſafe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, that ſtill the Scholar goeth a ſtep further then his Teacher. So it hath proved in former times, <hi>Luther,</hi> and no doubt many of thoſe who did imbrace his errors, in the firſt edition of them, yet lived and dyed in the true faith of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:159091:24"/>Chriſt, but the ſucceeding generations (inheriting thoſe erroneous tenents, which they had drawn from their godly forefathers, but not their godlineſſe) proved hereticks and ſchiſmaticks to this day. So it hath been in the Churches of <hi>Rome,</hi> and others, and ſo wee may juſtly feare in theſe Churches in <hi>New England,</hi> howſoever that many that now adhere to theſe Familiſticall opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are indeed truely godly, and (no doubt) ſhall perſevere ſo to the end, yet the next generation, which ſhall bee trained up under ſuch doctrines, will bee in great danger to prove plain Familiſts and Schiſmaticks. This diſcovery of a new rule of practiſe by immediate revelations, and the conſideration of ſuch dangerous conſequences, which have and might follow thereof, occaſioned the Court to diſarm all ſuch of that party, as had their hands to the Petition, and ſome others, who had openly defended the ſame, except they ſhould give ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the Magiſtrates therein; which ſome preſently did, others made a great queſtion about it, for bringing in their armes, but they were too weake to ſtand it out.</p>
               <p>Thus it pleaſed the Lord to heare the prayers of his afflicted people (whoſe ſoules had wept in ſecret, for the reproach which was caſt upon the Churches of the Lord Jeſus in this Countrey, by occaſion of the diviſions which were grown amongſt us, though the vanity of ſome weake minds, which cannot ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly affect any thing long, except it bee offered them under ſome renewed ſhape) and by the care and indevour of the wiſe and faithfull Miniſters of the Churches, aſſiſted by the Civill authority, to diſcover this Maſter-piece of the old Serpent, and to break the brood by ſcattering the Leaders, under whoſe conduct hee had prepared ſuch Ambuſhment, as in all reaſon would ſoon have driven Chriſt and Goſpel out of <hi>New England,</hi> (though to the ruine of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments themſelves, as well as others) and to the repoſſeſſing of Satan in his ancient Kingdom; It is the Lords work, and it is marvellous in our eyes. Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> is now gone to <hi>Paſcal,</hi> Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon</hi> is confined in a private houſe, till the ſeaſon of the yeer ſhall bee fit for her departure, ſome of thoſe whom God hath left to bee moſt ſtrongly deluded, are preparing to follow them, and wee hope the Lord will open the eyes of the reſt, and perſwade them to joyn again with their ſometime deare and moſt beloved brethren, that peace and truth may again flouriſh in <hi>New England, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the Court had thus proceeded, ſome of the Churches dealt with ſuch of their members as were found guilty of theſe erroneous and ſeditious practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the Church of <hi>Roxbury</hi> (after much pains and patience to reduce them) excommunicated five or ſix; and the Church of <hi>Boſton,</hi> by the ſolicitation of ſome of the Elders of the other Churches, proceeded againſt Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon,</hi> the manner and iſſue whereof is ſet down in the next.</p>
               <div type="narrative">
                  <p>AT <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New England,</hi> upon the 17. day of <hi>October</hi> 1637. the wife of one <hi>William Dyer,</hi> ſometimes a Citizen &amp; Millener of <hi>London,</hi> a very proper
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:159091:25"/>and comely young woman, was delivered of a large woman childe, it was ſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, about two moneths before her time, the childe having life a few houres before the delivery, but ſo monſtrous and miſ-ſhapen, as the like hath ſcarce been heard of: it had no head but a face, which ſtood ſo low upon the breſt, as the eares (which were like an Apes) grew upon the ſhoulders.</p>
                  <p>The eyes ſtood farre out, ſo did the mouth, the noſe was hooking upward, the breſt and back was full of ſharp prickles, like a Thornback, the navell and all the belly with the diſtinction of the ſex, were, where the lower part of the back and hips ſhould have been, and thoſe back parts were on the ſide the face ſtood.</p>
                  <p>The arms and hands, with the thighs and legges, were as other childrens, but in ſtead of toes, it had upon each foot three claws, with talons like a young fowle.</p>
                  <p>Upon the back above the belly it had two great holes, like mouthes, and in each of them ſtuck out a piece of fleſh.</p>
                  <p>It had no forehead, but in the place thereof, above the eyes, foure hornes, whereof two were above an inch long, hard, and ſharpe, the other two were ſomewhat ſhorter.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Many things were obſervable in the birth and diſcovery of this Monſter.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. The Father and Mother were of the higheſt forme of our refined Familiſts, and very active in maintaining their party, and in reproaching ſome of the Elders, and others, who did oppoſe thoſe errors.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Midwife, one <hi>Hawkins</hi> wife of St. <hi>Ives,</hi> was notorious for familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with the devill, and now a prime Familiſt.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. This Monſter was concealed by three perſons above five moneths.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. The occaſion of concealing it was very ſtrange, for moſt of the women who were preſent at the womans travaile, were ſuddenly taken with ſuch a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent vomiting, and purging, without eating or drinking of any thing, as they were forced to goe home, others had their children taken with convulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (which they had not before, nor ſince) and ſo were ſent for home, ſo as none were left at the time of the birth, but the Midwife and two other, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one fell aſleepe.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. At ſuch time as the child dyed (which was about two houres before the birth) the bed wherein the mother lay ſhook ſo violently, as all which were in the roome perceived it.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. The after birth wherein the childe was, had prickles on the inſide like thoſe on the childes breſt.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. The manner of the diſcovery was very ſtrange alſo, for it was that very day Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon</hi> was caſt out of the Church for her monſtrous errours, and notorious falſchood; for being commanded to depart the Aſſembly, Miſtris <hi>Dyer</hi> accompanied her, which a ſtranger obſerving, asked another what wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:159091:25"/>that was, the other anſwered, it was the woman who had the Monſter, which one of the Church of <hi>Boſton</hi> hearing, enquired about it from one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and at length came to Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon,</hi> with one of the Elders of the Church, to whom ſhee revealed the truth of the thing in generall onely; this comming to the Governours eare, hee called another of the Magiſtrates and ſent for the Midwife, and (in the preſence of the Elder, to whom Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon</hi> had revealed it) they examined her, who at firſt confeſſed it was a monſtrous birth, but concealed the horns and claws, and ſome other parts, till being ſtraitly charged, and told it ſhould bee taken up, and viewed, then ſhee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed all, yet for further aſſurance, the childe was taken up, and though it were much corrupted, yet the horns, and claws, and holes in the back, and ſome ſcales, &amp;c. were found and ſeen of above a hundred perſons.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. The Father of this Monſter, having been forth of the Town, about a Moneth, and comming home juſt at this time, was upon the Lords day (by an unexpected occaſion) called before the Church for ſome of his monſtrous opinions, as the Chriſt and the Church together, are the new creature, there is no inherent righteouſneſſe in Chriſtians, <hi>Adam</hi> was not made after Gods I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, &amp;c. which hee openly maintained, yet with ſuch ſhuffling, and equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating, as hee came under admonition, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:159091:26"/>
               <head>A briefe Apologie in defence of the generall proceedings of the Court, holden at <hi>Boſton</hi> the ninth day of the firſt moneth, 1626. againſt Mr. <hi>J. VVheelwright</hi> a member there, by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of a Sermon delivered there in the ſame Congregation.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as ſome of the Members of the Court (both of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Deputies) did diſſent from the major part, in the judgement of the cauſe of Mr. <hi>Wheelwright,</hi> and divers others have ſince cenſured the proceedings againſt him as unjuſt, or (at beſt) over haſty, for maintaining of which cenſures, many untruths are like to be ſpread abroad, whereby the moſt equall Judges may be in danger of prejudice; and ſo the honour not of the Court onely, but alſo of the tryall and juſtice it ſelfe may be blemiſhed: It is thought needfull to make this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Declaration of all the proceedings, with the reaſons and grounds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſo farre as concerneth the clearing of the juſtice of the Court. As for ſuch paſſages as fell by occaſion, and are too large to be here inſerted, ſuch as deſire to know them, may receive ſatisfaction from three or foure of <hi>Boſton</hi> (being Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> his ſpeciall friends) who tooke all by Characters (we doubt not) will give a true report thereof; As for ſuch as have taken offence, that the cauſe was not firſt referred to the Church, we deſire them to conſider theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This caſe was not matter of conſcience, but of a civill nature, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt proper for this Court, to take Cognizance of, and the rather for the ſpeciall contempt which had beene offered to the Court therein, and which the Church could not judge of. 2. In ſome caſes of religious nature, as mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt hereſie, notorious blaſphemy, &amp;c. the Civill power may proceed, <hi>Eccleſia inconſulta,</hi> and that by the judgement of all the Miniſters. 3. It had beene a vaine thing to referre a cauſe to the judgement of thoſe who had openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared their prejudice therein, both in the Court and otherwiſe, as by two Petitions under the hands of moſt of them, delivered into the Court on his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, did plainely appeare. 4. The heat of contention and uncharitable cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures which began to over-ſpread the Countrey, and that chiefely by occaſion of that Sermon, and the like miſcarriages, did require that the Civill power
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:159091:26"/>ſhould ſpeedily allay that heat, and beare witneſſe againſt all ſeditious courſes, tending to the overthrow of truth and peace amongſt us: this onely by way of entrance, to the matter which now followeth.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of the Court, the Deputies upon the ſame of a Sermon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> (upon the firſt day) which was ſuppoſed to tend to ſedition, and diſturbance of the publike peace, deſired that he might be ſent for, which the Court aſſenting unto, one of the Magiſtrates (his ſpeciall friend) undertooke to give him notice thereof, and accordingly at the next meeting he was in the Towne, ready to appeare, when he ſhould be called for, which was not till two or three dayes after, and then he was ſent for (not by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall, as the uſuall manner is; but) by one of the Deputies his intimate friend upon his appearance he was made acquainted with the cauſe why he was ſent for, <hi>viz.</hi> To ſatisfie the Court about ſome paſſages in his Sermon, which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be offenſive, and therewith a copy of it was produced, and he was deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded whether he would owne it: whereupon he drew forth another copy which he delivered into the Court, as a true copy, (for the ſubſtance of it) ſo he was diſmiſſed very gently, and deſired to be ready when he ſhould be called for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
               <p>The next day he was againe ſent for by the former meſſenger: About this time a Petition was delivered into the Court, under the hands of above forty perſons, being moſt of the Church of <hi>Boſton</hi> (being none of the Petitions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, which were delivered after) to this effect, that as free-men they might be admitted to be preſent in the Court in cauſes of judicature, and that the Court would declare whether they might proceed in caſes of conſcience, without referring them firſt to the Church. To this the Court anſwered on the backſide of the Petition, that they did conceive the Petition was without juſt ground, for the firſt part of it, the Court had never uſed privacie in Judiciall proceedings, but in preparation thereto by way of examination of the party, &amp;c. they might and would uſe their liberty, as they ſhould ſee cauſe; and for the other part of the Petition, when any matter of conſcience ſhould come before them, they would adviſe what were fit to be done in it.</p>
               <p>When Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> came in, the Court was private, and then they told him they had conſidered of his Sermon, and were deſirous to aske him ſome queſtions which might tend to cleare his meaning, about ſuch paſſages therein as ſeemed offenſive; he demanded whether he were ſent for as an innocent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or as guilty? It was anſwered neither, but as ſuſpected onely; Then he demanded, who were his accuſers? It was anſwered, his Sermon; (which was there in Court) being acknowledged by himſelfe they might thereupon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, <hi>ex officio:</hi> at this word great exception was taken, as if the Court inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the courſe of the High Commiſſion, &amp;c. It was anſwered that the word <hi>ex officio</hi> was very ſafe and proper, ſignifying no more but the authority or duty of the Court, and that there was no cauſe of offence, ſeeing the Court did not examine him by any compulſory meanes, as by oath, impriſonment,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:159091:27"/>or the like, but onely deſired him for better ſatisfaction to anſwer ſome queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but he ſtill refuſed, yet at laſt through perſwaſion of ſome of his friends, he ſeemed content; The queſtion then put to him was, whether before his Sermon he did not know, that moſt of the Miniſters in this juriſdiction did teach that doctrine which be in his Sermon called a Covenant of works; to this he ſaid, he did not desire to anſwer, and hereupon ſome cried out, that the Court went about to enſnare him, and to make him to accuſe himſelfe, and that this queſtion was not about the matter of his Sermon, &amp;c. Upon this he refuſed to anſwer any further, ſo he was diſmiſſed till the afternoone; The reaſon why the Court demanded that queſtion of him, was not to draw mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from himſelfe whereupon to proceed againſt him, neither was there any need, for upon a conference of the Miniſters not long before there had beene large diſpute betweene ſome of them and himſelfe about that point of eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Juſtification by Sanctification, ſo as the court might ſoone have convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him by witneſſes, if they had intended to proceed againſt him upon that ground.</p>
               <p>In the afternoone he was ſent for againe in the ſame manner as before, and the Miniſters alſo being in the Towne, and come thither to conferre together for further diſcovery of the ground of the diſterences which were in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey about the Covenant of Grace, &amp;c. they were deſired to be preſent alſo in the Court, to beare witneſſe of the proceedings in the caſe, and to give their advice as the Court (upon occaſion) ſhould require: ſo the doores being ſet open for all that would to come in (and there was a great Aſſembly) and Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> being willed to ſit downe by the Miniſters, his Sermon was produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and many paſſages thereof was read to him, which for the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding we have digeſted into this order following.</p>
               <p>He therein deſcribeth two Covenants, the Covenant of Grace and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Works; the Covenant of Grace he deſcribeth to be, when in the point of Juſtification and the knowledge of this our Juſtification by Faith, there is nothing revealed but Chriſt Jeſus; but if men thinke to be ſaved, becauſe they ſee ſome worke of Sanctification in themſelves, as hungring and thirſting, &amp;c. this is a Covenant of Works; if men have revealed to them ſome work of righteouſneſſe, as love to the brethren, &amp;c. and hereupon come to be aſſured that they are in a good eſtate, this is not the aſſurance of Faith, for Faith hath Criſt revealed for the object, therefore if the aſſurance of a mans Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be by Faith, as a Work, it is not Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Having thus deſcribed thoſe who goe under a Covenant of Works, he pronounceth them to be enemies to Chriſt, to be Antichriſts, to be fleſh op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſpirit; ſuch as will certainly perſecute thoſe who hold forth the truth, and the wayes of Grace; he reſembleth them to the Philiſtims, who ſtop up with the earth of their owne inventions, the Wels of true beleevers; he reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth them alſo to <hi>Herod,</hi> who would have killed Chriſt ſo ſoone as he was borne, and to <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> who did kill Chriſt when he came once to ſhew
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:159091:27"/>forth himſelfe, and would have kept him eternally in the grave; he further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth them out of the ſecond Pſalme, to be the people of God as the Jewes were, and ſuch as would take away the true Chriſt and put in falſe Chriſts, to deceive if it were poſſible the very elect; he alſo deſcribeth them by that in <hi>Cant.</hi> 10.6. they make the children of Grace keepers of the Vineyard, they make them travell under the burden of the Covenant of Works, which doth cauſe Chriſt many times from them. He commeth after to a uſe of exhortation, wherein he ſtirreth up all thoſe of his ſide to a ſpirituall combate, to prepare for battel, and come out and fight againſt the enemies of the Lord; (thoſe under a Covenant of Works) he ſhewes whom he meaneth thus to excite, alluding to <hi>Davids</hi> valiant men, to <hi>Baruch, Deborah, Jael,</hi> and all the men of <hi>Jſrael,</hi> and bind them hereunto under the curſe of <hi>Meroz;</hi> He further exhorteth them to ſtand upon their guard, &amp;c. by alluding to the 600. valiant men, who kept watch about the bed of <hi>Solomon,</hi> a type of Chriſt; then he encourageth thoſe of his ſide againſt ſuch difficulties as might be objected, as 1. If the enemies ſhall oppoſe the way of God, they muſt lay the more load on them, and kill them with the Word of the Lord; and there he alludeth to thoſe places which ſpeak of giving the Saints power over nations, binding Kings in chaines, and of thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing inſtruments with teeth, and foretels their flight by that in <hi>Eſay</hi> 21.15. They ſhall flee from the ſword, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though the enemies under a Covenant of Works be many and ſtrong, (as he confeſſeth they are) yet they ought not to fear, for the battel is the Lords, this he enforceth by that in <hi>Joſh.</hi> 23.10. One of you ſhall chaſe a thouſand, and that of <hi>Jonathan</hi> and his armour-bearer.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Againſt tenderneſſe of heart, which they might have towards ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Covenant of Works, as are exceeding holy and ſtrict in their way, he animateth his party by perſwading them, that ſuch are the greateſt enemies to Chriſt; this he ſeekes to illuſtrate by reſembling ſuch in their zeale to <hi>Paul</hi> when he was a perſecutor, and in their devotion to thoſe who expelled <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> out of <hi>Antioch.</hi> He taketh it for granted that theſe holy men truſt in their righteouſneſſe, and that it thruſteth out the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes and foretels from <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33. They ſhall die, and that their righteouſneſſe is accurſed, yet they transforme themſelves (ſaith he) into Angels of light.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That his party might not feare leſt he ſhould breake the rule of meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. he bringeth in the example of <hi>Stephen, Act.</hi> 7.58. and the example of Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44. and <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.23.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To thoſe who might feare, leſt this ſtrife ſhould cauſe a combuſtion in Church and Common-wealth, he anſwers and tells them plainely it will doe ſo, but yet to uphold their hearts, he armes them with the prediction of Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.49. and tells them that it is the deſire of the Saints, that that fire were kindled, and with that in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 9.5. which he interprets of <hi>Michael</hi> and the Angells, and with that in <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2. and by that in the Revelation, the whore muſt be burnt.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:159091:28"/>6. Hee armes them againſt perſecution by exhorting them not to love their lives unto the death, but be willing to be killed like ſheepe, ſeeing it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hold forth the truth of God with externall peace and quietneſſe: This he enforceth by the example of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> who ſlew more at his death then in his life.</p>
               <p>Theſe paſſages of his Sermon being openly read, Maſter <hi>Wheelwright</hi> did acknowledge and juſtifie the ſame, and being demanded (either then or before) whether by thoſe under a Covenant of workes hee did meane any of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and other Chriſtians in thoſe Churches, he anſwered, that if he were ſhewed any that walked in ſuch a way, as he had deſcribed to be a Covenant of workes, them he did meane. Here divers ſpeeches paſſed up and downe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there was no ſpeciall notice taken, as not materiall to the purpoſe in hand.</p>
               <p>The Court proceeded alſo to examine ſome witneſſes about another Sermon of his, whereat much offence had alſo beene taken, and not without cauſe, (as appeared to the Court) for in that he ſeemed to ſcare men not onely from le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall righteouſneſſe, but even from faith and repentance, as if that alſo were a way of the Covenant of workes; but this being matter of Doctrine, the Court paſſed it by for the preſent, onely they (and the Miniſters preſent, divers of them) declared their griefe to ſee ſuch opinions riſen in the Country of ſo dangerous conſequence, and ſo directly croſſing the ſcope of the Goſpell, (as was conceived) and it was retorted upon him which he in his Sermon chargeth his adverſe party with, (though uncharitably and untruly) when he ſaith they would take away the true Chriſt, that to make good ſuch a doctrine as he held forth (to common intendment) muſt needes call for a new Chriſt and a new Goſpell, for ſure the old would not owne or juſtifie it.</p>
               <p>Then the Court propounded a queſtion to the Miniſters, which (becauſe they deſired time of conſideration to make anſwer unto) was given them in writing upon the outſide of Maſter <hi>Wheelwrights</hi> Sermon, in theſe words; <hi>Whether by that which you have heard concerning Maſter</hi> Wheelwrights <hi>Sermon, and that which was witneſſed concerning him, yee doe conceive that the Miniſters in this Country doe walke in and teach ſuch a way of Salvation and evidencing thereof, as he deſcribeth, and accounteth to be a Covenant of workes?</hi> To this queſtion (being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine called for into the Court the next morning) they returned an affirmative anſwer, in the very words of the queſtion, adding withall, that they would not be underſtood, that their doctrine and Maſter <hi>Wheelwrights</hi> about Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Salvation, and evidencing thereof, did differ in all things, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the point preſented, and debated now in Court, and that of this their anſwer they were ready to give reaſons when the Court ſhould demand them, and that to this they all conſented, except their brother the teacher of <hi>Boſton:</hi> After this (by leave of the Court) the Miniſters all ſpake one by one in order, ſome more largely, laying open by ſolid arguments and notorious examples, the great dangers that the Churches and Civill State were falne into, by the differences which were growne amongſt us in matters of Religion, offering
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:159091:28"/>themſelves withall to employ all their ſtudies to effect a reconciliation, ſhewing alſo their deſires that Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> would be with them, when they ſhould meete for this purpoſe, and blaming his former ſtrangeneſſe as a poſſible occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theſe differences of judgement. Others ſpake more briefely, but conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the former; and all of them (as they had occaſion to ſpeake to Mr. <hi>Wheelwright,</hi> or to make mention of him) uſed him with all humanity and reſpect; what his carriage was towards them againe, thoſe who were preſent may judge, as they ſaw cauſe.</p>
               <p>The matters objected againſt Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> being recollected, and put to the vote, the opinion of the Court was, that he had run into ſedition and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Civill authority, which accordingly was recorded to the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and he was enjoyned to appeare at the next generall Court to abide their further ſentence herein. And whereas motion was made of enjoyning him ſilence in the meane time, the Miniſters were deſired to deliver their advice what the Court might doe in ſuch a caſe: Their anſwer was, that they could not give a cleare reſolution of the queſtion at the preſent, but for Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> they deſired that the Court would rather referre him to the Church of <hi>B.</hi> to deale with him for that matter; which accordingly was done, and ſo he was diſmiſſed: ſuch of the Magiſtrates and Deputies, as had not concurred with the major part in the vote, (ſome of them) moved that the diſſent might be recorded, (but it was denyed) as a courſe never uſed in this or any ſuch Court. Afterward they tendered a Proteſtation, which was alſo refuſed, becauſe therein they had juſtified Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> as a faithfull Miniſter of the Lord Jeſus, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the Court for undue proceeding; but this was offered them, that if they would write downe the words of the record, and ſubſcribe their diſſent without laying ſuch aſperſion upon the Court, it ſhould be received.</p>
               <p>Although the ſimple narration of theſe proceedings might be ſufficient to juſtifie the Court in what they have done, eſpecially with theſe of this juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who have taken notice of the paſſages in the generall Court in <hi>Decem.</hi> laſt, yet for ſatisfaction of others to whom this caſe may be otherwiſe preſented by ſame or miſreport, we will ſet downe ſome grounds and reaſons thereof, ſome whereof were expreſſed in the Court, and others (though not publickly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted upon, yet) well conceived by ſome, as further motives to leade their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to doe as they did.</p>
               <p>And, 1. It is to be obſerved, that the noted differences in point of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the Churches here, are about the Covenant of workes, in oppoſition to the Covenant of grace; in clearing whereof much diſpute hath beene, whether ſanctification be any evidence of juſtification.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That before Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> came into this country (which is not yet two yeares ſince) there was no ſtrife (at leaſt in publick obſervation) about that point.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That he did know (as himſelfe confeſſed) that divers of the Miniſters here were not of his Judgement in thoſe points, and that the publiſhing of them,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:159091:29"/>would cauſe diſturbance in the Country, and yet he would never conferre with the Miniſters about them, that thereby he might have gained them to his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, (if it had beene the truth) or at leaſt have manifeſted ſome care of the publick peace, which he rather ſeemed to ſlight, when being demanded in the Court a reaſon of ſuch his failing, hee anſwered that he ought not to conſult with fleſh and bloud, about the publiſhing of that truth whcih he had received from God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It was well knowne to him that the Magiſtrates and Deputies were very ſenſible of thoſe differences, and ſtudious of pacifying ſuch mindes as began to be warme and apt to contention about them, and for this end at the ſaid Court in <hi>December,</hi> (where theſe differences and alienations of minde through raſh cenſures, &amp;c. were ſadly complained of) they had called in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and (Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> being preſent) had deſired their advice for diſcovery of ſuch dangers, as did threaten us hereby, and their helpe for preventing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and it was then thought needefull, to appoint a ſolemne day of humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as for other occaſions more remote, ſo eſpecially) for this which more neerely concerned us, and at this time this very point of evidencing juſtification by ſanctification ſet into ſome debate, and Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> being preſent ſpake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, though he well diſcerned that the judgement of moſt of the Magiſtrates and neere all the Miniſters cloſed with the affirmative.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That upon the ſaid faſt (Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> being deſired by the Church to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe as a private brother, by way of Prophecy) when Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> teaching in the afternoon out of <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58.4. had ſhewed that it was not a fit worke for a day of Faſt, to move ſtrife &amp; debate, to provoke to contention, &amp;c. but by all means to labour pacification and reconciliation, and therein had beſtowed much time, and many forcible arguments, yet Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> ſpeaking after him, taught as is here before mentioned, wholly omitting thoſe particular occaſions which the Court intended, nay rather reproving them, in teaching that the onely cauſe of Faſting, was the abſence of Chriſt, &amp;c. and ſo notwithſtanding the occaſion of the day, Mr. <hi>Cottons</hi> example, the intent of the Court for procuriug peace, he ſtirred up the people to contention, and that with more then ordinary ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemency. Now if any man will equally weigh the proceedings of the Court and theſe obſervations together, we hope it will appeare that Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> was juſtly convict of ſedition and contempt of authority, and ſuch as have not leiſure or will to compare them together, may onely reade that which here fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, and receive ſatisfaction thereby, carrying this along with them, that the acts of authority holding forth the face, and ſtampe of a divine ſentence ſhould not be leſſe regarded then the actions of any private brother, which a good man will view on all foure ſides before he judge them to be evill.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Sedition and contempt are laid to his charge.</label>
               </p>
               <p>Sedition doth properly ſignifie a going aſide to make a party, and is right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcribed by the Poet, (for it is lawfull to fetch the meaning of words from
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:159091:29"/>humane authority) <hi>In mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> populo cum ſaepe cooria eſt ſeditio ſaevitque animis,</hi> &amp;c. whence it doth appeare that when the minds of the people being aſſembled are kindled or made fierce upon ſome ſuddaine occaſion, ſo as they fall to take part one againſt another, this is ſedition; for when that <hi>furor,</hi> which doth <hi>arma miniſtrare,</hi> is once kindled, the ſedition is begun, though it come not to its perfection, till <hi>faces et ſaxa volant: Tully</hi> ſaith, <hi>Seditionem, eſſe diſſenſionem omnium inter ſe, cum eunt alii in aliud,</hi> when the people diſſent in opinion and goe ſeverall wayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſidore</hi> ſaith, <hi>Seditioſus eſt, qui diſſentionem animorum facit &amp; diſcordias gignit,</hi> He that ſets mens minds at difference, and begets ſtrife: And if we look into the Scripture we ſhall find examples of ſedition agreeing to theſe deſcriptions. The uproare moved by <hi>Demetrius, Acts</hi> 19. was ſedition, yet he neither took up armes, nor perſwaded others ſo to doe, but onely induced the minds of the people, and made them fierce againſt the Apoſtles, by telling them they were enemies to <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Epheſians. Korah</hi> and his company moved a moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſedition, yet they did not ſtirre up the people to fight, onely they went apart and drew others to them againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> here was nothing but words, and that by a Levite, who might ſpeake by his place, but it coſt more then words before it was pacified. Now in our preſent caſe, did not Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> make ſides when he proclaimed all to be under a Covenant of works, who did not follow him (ſtep by ſtep) in his deſcription of the Covenant of Grace? did he not make himſelfe a party on the other ſide, by often uſing theſe and the like words, We, us? Did he not labour to heat the minds of the people, and to make them fierce againſt thoſe of that ſide, which he oppoſed (and whereof he knew that moſt of the Magiſtrates and Miniſters had declared themſelves) when with the greateſt fervency of ſpirit and voyce, he proclaimes them Antichriſts, ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Philiſtims, <hi>Herod, Pilate,</hi> perſecuting Jewes, and ſtirred up them on his part to fight with them, to lay load on them, to burne them, to threſh them, to bind them in chaines and fetters, to kill them and vexe their hearts, and that under the paine of the curſe of <hi>Meroz? Tantaene animis caeleſtibus irae?</hi> would one thinke that any heavenly ſpirit could have breathed ſo much anger, when an Angel would have given milder language to the Devill himſelfe? and all this without vouchſaſing one argument to convince theſe enemies of their evil way, or one word of admonition or advice to themſelves, to draw them out of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. But it is objected, that he expreſſed his meaning to be of a ſpirituall fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and killing, &amp;c. with the ſword of the ſpirit onely. It is granted he did ſo, yet his inſtances of illuſtration, or rather enforcement, were of another na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as of <hi>Moſes</hi> killing the Egyptian in defence of his brother, <hi>Sampſon</hi> loſing his life with the Philiſtims, the fight of <hi>Jonathan</hi> and his armour-bearer, and of <hi>Davids</hi> worthies, <hi>Baruc</hi> and <hi>Jael,</hi> &amp;c. theſe obtained their victories with ſwords and hammers, &amp;c. And ſuch are no ſpirituall weapons, ſo that if his intent were not to ſtirre up to open force and armes (neither doe we ſuſpect him of any ſuch purpoſe, otherwiſe then by conſequent) yet his reading and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:159091:30"/>might have told him, how dangerous it is to heat peoples affections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their oppoſites, a mind inflamed with indignation (among ſome people) would have beene more apt to have drawne their ſwords by the authority of the examples he held forth for the encouragement, then to have beene kept to ſpirituall weapons, by the reſtraining without cautions, ſuch as cannot diſpute for Chriſt with <hi>Steven,</hi> will be ready to draw their ſwords for him, like <hi>Peter;</hi> for <hi>furor arms miniſtrat,</hi> like him who when he could not by any ſentence in the Bible confute an Heretick, could make uſe of the whole booke to break his head; we might hold forth inſtances more then enough. The warres in <hi>Germany</hi> for theſe hundred yeeres aroſe from diſſentions in Religion, and though in the beginning of the contention, they drew out onely the ſword of the Spirit, yet it was ſoone changed into a ſword of ſteele; ſo was it among the confederate Cantons of <hi>Helvetia,</hi> which were ſo many Townes as neerely combined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as ours here; ſo was it alſo in the <hi>Netherlands</hi> betweene the Orthodox and the <hi>Arminians;</hi> ſo hath it beene betweene the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> and <hi>Lutherans:</hi> In every place we find that the contentions began firſt by diſputations and Sermons, and when the minds of the people were once ſet on fire by reproachfull termes of intendiary ſpirits, they ſoone ſet to blowes, and had alwayes a tragicall and boudy iſſue; And to cleare this objection, Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> profeſſed before hand, what he looked for, <hi>viz.</hi> that his doctrine would cauſe combuſtions even in the Common-wealth, as well as in the Churches, which he could not have feared if he had ſuppoſed (as in charity he well might) that thoſe who were ſet over the people here in both States were indeed true Chriſtians; yea he not onely confeſſeth his expectation, but his earneſt deſire alſo of ſuch combuſtions and diſturbances, when he ſaith that it is the Saints deſire to have the fire kindled, as if hee were come among Turks or Papiſts, and not among the Churches of Chriſt, amongſt whom <hi>Paul</hi> laboured to quench all fire of contention, but with the <hi>Corinthians, Romans,</hi> and <hi>Galatians,</hi> and wiſhed that thoſe were cut off who troubled them, ſetting a mark upon ſuch as made diviſion, and a note of a carnall mind: therefore this objection will not ſave him, his offence is yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe, hee did intend to trouble our peace, and hee hath effected it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was a contempt of that authority which required every man to ſtudy Peace and Truth, and therefore it was a ſeditious contempt, in that hee ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up others; to joyn in the diſturbance of that peace, which hee was bound by ſolemn Oath to preſerve.</p>
               <p>But here hee puts in a plea, that hee did take the only right way for Peace, by holding out the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the Covenant of free Grace, for without Chriſt there is no peace, but get Chriſt and wee have all.</p>
               <p>To this wee reply, firſt, Wee would demand of him what hee accounts a hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forth a Covenant of Grace? for ſaving that hee ſaith, this is a Covenant of Grace, that is a Covenant of Works, no man can diſcerne any ſuch thing by his proofes, for there is not any one argument in his Sermon to convince the judgement that ſo it is, and if wee ſearch the Scripture, wee find in the Old
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:159091:30"/>Teſtament, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. the Covenant of Grace to bee this, I will write my Law in their hearts, or, I will bee their God, &amp;c. and in the New Teſtament, wee find, Hee that beleeves in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall bee ſaved, and that it is of Faith, that it might bee of grace; but other Covenant of Grace then theſe, or to the ſame effect, are not in our Bibles.</p>
               <p>Again, Though it bee true, that get Chriſt and wee have all in ſome reſpect, yet wee muſt remember him of what hee ſaid with the ſame breath, that Truth and externall Peace cannot poſſibly ſtand together, how then would hee have us beleeve, that ſuch a holding forth Chriſt ſhould bring the deſired peace? This is ſomewhat like the Jewiſh <hi>Corban,</hi> I will give to God, and hee ſhall help my Parents, or as when a poore man ſtands in need of ſuch reliefe, as I might give him, inſtead there of I pray to God to bleſſe him, and tell him that the bleſſing of God maketh rich, or, as I give a Lawyer a Fee to plead my cauſe, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure mee Juſtice, and when the day of hearing comes, hee makes a long ſpeech in commending the juſtice of the King, and perſwading mee to get his favour, becauſe hee is the fountain of Juſtice; This is to reprove the wiſdome of God, by looking that the ſupreme and firſt cauſe ſhould produce all effects, without the uſe of ſubordinate acd neerer cauſes and means; ſo a man ſhould live out his full time by Gods decree only, without meat or medicine; this plea therefore will not hold, let us heare another.</p>
               <p>It is objected, that the Magiſtrates may not appoint a meſſenger of God, what hee ſhould teach: admit ſo much, yet hee may limit him what hee may not teach, if hee forbid him to teach hereſy or ſedition, &amp;c. hee incurres as well a contempt in teaching that which hee was forbidden, as ſins in teaching that which is evill. Beſides, every truth is not ſeaſonable at all times. Chriſt tels his Diſciples that hee had many things to teach them, but they could not beare them then, <hi>Job.</hi> 16.12. and God giveth his Prophets the tongue of the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they may know how to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50, 40. and if for every thing there bee a ſeaſon, then for every Doctrine, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.1. The abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of the ceremoniall Law was a Truth which the Apoſtles were to teach, yet there was a ſeaſon when <hi>Paul</hi> did refrain it, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.24. and the ſame <hi>Paul</hi> would not circumciſe <hi>Titus,</hi> though hee did <hi>Timothy,</hi> ſo the difference of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and places, made a difference in the ſeaſon of the doctrine: and if Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> had looked upon the words which followed in his Text, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.16, 17. hee might have learned that ſuch a Sermon would as ill ſuite the ſeaſon, as old bottles doe new Wine, and by that in <hi>Eſay</hi> before mentioned, hee might have known that the Spirit of God doth teach his ſervants to diſcern of ſeaſons, as well as of truths; for if there be ſuch a point in wiſdom, as men call diſcretion, ſure, Religion (which maketh truely wiſe) doth not deprive the ſervants of God of the right uſe thereof. When <hi>Paul</hi> was to deale with the ſorcerer, who did oppoſe his doctrine, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. hee cals him the childe of the devill, &amp;c. but when hee anſwered <hi>Feſtus,</hi> (who told him hee was madde, and rejected his doctrine alſo) hee uſeth him gently, and with termes of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:159091:31"/>reſpect. Though <hi>Steven</hi> cals the Jews ſtiffenecked, and of uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed hearts, &amp;c. as knowing them to bee malitious and obſtinate enemies to Chriſt, yet <hi>Paul</hi> directs <hi>Timothy</hi> (being to deale with ſuch as were not paſt hope, though they did oppoſe his Doctrine for the preſent) not to ſtrive, but to uſe all gentleneſſe, inſtructing them with meekneſſe, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. The Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> when hee ſpeaks to <hi>Jehoram</hi> very roughly, as one not worthy to bee look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, yet hee ſhews a different reſpect of <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> though hee were then out of his way, and under a ſin, for which hee had been formerly reproved, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 3. Chriſt himſelfe (though hee ſharply reproveth the Phariſees, &amp;c. yet hee inſtructeth <hi>Nicodemus</hi> gently, when hee objected againſt his doctrine, and that ſomewhat rudely, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. The Apoſtles would not forbeare to Preach Chriſt, though Rulers forbad them, <hi>Act.</hi> 3. yet another Prophet forbare at another ſeaſon at the command of King <hi>Amaſia,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25. ſo wee ſee that this plea of Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> is as weak as the former, and will not excuſe him from contempt.</p>
               <p>If it bee yet objected, that his Sermon was not all for contention, ſeeing hee raiſed and preſſed an uſe of brotherly love, wee grant hee did ſo, but it was <hi>ejuſdem farinae,</hi> a loafe of the ſame leaven with the other, for hee applyeth it to thoſe of his own party, to perſwade them to hold together, and help one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt thoſe of the other party, whom hee ſetteth forth as their oppoſites and encourageth them thereto by the example of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who in love to his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, killed the <hi>Aegyptian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A further objection hath been made againſt the proceedings of the Court, as if Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> had not a lawfull tryall, as not being put upon a Jury of freemen. But the anſwer to this is eaſie, it being wel known to all ſuch as have underſtanding of matters of this nature, that ſuch Courts as have power to make and abrogate Laws, are tyed to no other Orders, but their own, and to no other rule but Truth and Juſtice, and why thrice twelve men ſitting as Judges in a Court, ſhould bee more ſubject to partiality then twelve ſuch called as a Jury to the barre, let others judge.</p>
               <p>Now if ſome ſhall gather from that which is here before mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> that every truth is not ſeaſonable at all times, if wee ſhall grant that what Maſter <hi>Wheelwright</hi> delivered was the truth, wee muſt deſire him to take onely ſo much as wee granted, <hi>viz.</hi> by way of ſuppoſition onely; for letting paſſe (as wee ſaid) ſuch points as were meerly doctrinall, and not ripe for the Court (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending as yet in examination among the Elders) wee may ſafely deny that thoſe ſpeeches were truths, which the Court cenſured for contempt and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for a brother may fall ſo farre into diſobedience to the Goſpel, as there may bee cauſe to ſeparate from him, and to put him to ſhame, and yet hee is not to bee accounted an enemy, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3. Therefore when Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced ſuch (taking them at the worſt hee could make them) to bee ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, &amp;c. it was not according to the truth of the Goſpell. Againe, to incenſe and heate mens minds againſt their Brethren, before hee had convinced or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:159091:31"/>them, as being in an eſtate of enmity, &amp;c. is not to bee termed in any truth of the Goſpel; ſo likewiſe to bring extraordinary examples for ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary rules, as of <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44. to incite his party to the like practiſe againſt ſuch whoſe hearts they cannot judge of, as Chriſt could of theirs to whom hee ſpake, is as farre from the rule preſcribed to ordinary Miniſters, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. and to all Chriſtians, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. and <hi>Jam.</hi> 3 17. as that example of <hi>Elijah</hi> (by which the Apoſtles would have called for fire from heaven upon the Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans) was different from the Spirit whereof they were: ſo to reſemble ſuch among us, as profeſſe their faith in Chriſt only, &amp;c. and are in Church fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, and walk inoffenſively, ſubmitting to all the Lords Ordinances in Church and Common wealth, to reſemble ſuch to branded Reprobates, and arch-enemies of Chriſt, ſuch as <hi>Herod,</hi> &amp;c. wee ſuppoſe hath no warrant of Truth. Wee might inſtance in other like paſſages, as his ordinary inciting to ſpirituall combates, by examples of bodily fight and bloody victories, (being very unſutable) but theſe may ſuffice to prove that all hee ſpake was not true, and by this is the offence more aggravated, for if it were ſeditious only in the manner, it muſt needs bee much worſe, when the matter it ſelfe alſo was untrue.</p>
               <p>But if any ſhall yet pretend want of ſatisfaction, by all that hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, (for indeed it is beyond reaſon, how farre prejudice hath prevailed to captivate ſome Judgements, otherwiſe godly and wiſe) and ſhal object further, that his doctrines, &amp;c. were generall, and ſo could not bee intended of any particular perſons, wee deſire ſuch, firſt to remember what application Mr. <hi>Wh.</hi> made of the ſame in the open Court, <hi>viz.</hi> that hee did intend all ſuch as walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſuch a way. Then again, let the caſe bee put in a reverſed frame, ſome other had then taught, that all ſuch as deny that ſanctification (as it is held by the other party) is a good evidence of juſtification, and that ſay or have their aſſurance by faith, as a work of God in them have it in the way of the Goſpel, that theſe were enemies to Chriſt, &amp;c. Perſecutors of the way of grace, &amp;c. and ſhould have ſtirred up others againſt them, with like arguments, and vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy as Mr. <hi>Wheelwright</hi> did, there is no doubt but Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> and others of his opinion, would ſoone have pointed out thoſe who muſt neceſſarily have been intended by it: for it is well known that ſome proper adjunct, or ſome noted circumſtance may deſign a particular perſon or company, as well as names, ſo Chriſt points out <hi>Judas</hi> by the ſop, <hi>Paul</hi> the Jews, by thoſe of the circumciſion, and the Antichriſt, by That man of ſin, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But wee meet y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with another objection, <hi>viz.</hi> that diſturbance of unity is not ſedition, except it alſo lead to the hurt of utility.</p>
               <p>To this wee anſwer, firſt, that if it tend immediately to ſuch hurt, wee deny the truth of the propoſition; for if in the time of famine, a man ſhould ſtir up the people to fetch corn out of the houſes of ſuch as had it to ſpare, this were to an immediate publick good, yet it were ſedition. If <hi>Jeremy</hi> (when hee taught the Jews, that they ought to ſet free their Hebrew ſervants) had alſo
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:159091:32"/>incited the ſervants to free themſelves, this had not been free from ſedition, yet it had not been againſt publick utility: But they alledge the examples of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hojadah,</hi> who cauſed a diſturbance, yet without ſedition; wee anſwer, that caſe was very unlike to ours, for <hi>Jehojadah</hi> being High Prieſt, was alſo protector of the true King, and ſo chiefe Governour of the Civill State, and <hi>Athaliah</hi> being a meere uſurper, hee did no other, then if a lawfull King ſhould aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his Subjects to apprehend a Rebell; and though a Prince or Governour may raiſe a party to ſuppreſſe or withſtand publick enemies or other evils, yet it doth not follow that a private man, or a Miniſter of the Goſpel may do the like: we read <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.7. that hee raiſed a great aſſembly againſt thoſe who did oppreſſe their brethren, but wee read not that <hi>Ezra</hi> did ſo, upon the diſorders which hee complained of, and yet that which hee did in aſſembling of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for redreſſe, &amp;c. was by authority and counſell of the Nobles, <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That this courſe of Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> did tend directly to the great hinderance of publike utility, for when brethren ſhall looke one at another as enemies and perſecutors, &amp;c. and when people ſhall looke at their Rulers and Miniſters as ſuch, and as thoſe who goe about to take Chriſt and ſalvation from them, how ſhall they joyne together in any publike ſervice? how ſhall they cohabite and trade together? how hardly will they ſubmit to ſuch Over-ſeers? how will it hinder all affaires in Courts, in Townes, in Families, in Veſſels at Sea, &amp;c. and what can more threaten the diſſolution and ruine of Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth? Laſtly, if it be alleadged that ſuch warlike termes are uſed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles in a ſpirituall ſenſe, we deny it not, but we deſire that the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all manner of their applying then may be alſo conſidered, for <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. So fight I, &amp;c. I beate downe my body, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.12. Fight the good fight of faith, lay hold on eternall life, and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. and <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.1. there is ſpeech of the fight of our luſts, and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.11. he bids them put on armour, but it is to reſiſt the Devill, not fleſh and bloud, not to fight againſt their brethren, towards whom he forbids all bitterneſſe and clamour, &amp;c. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. And when he ſpeaks of ſpirituall weapons, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. he doth non draw them out againſt the perſons of brethren, but againſt high thoughts and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp;c. And if Mr. <hi>Wheel.</hi> had found out any ſuch among us, and planted his battery againſt them by ſound arguments, he had followed our Apoſtolike rule; Chriſt indeed threatneth to fight againſt the Nicholairans with the ſword of his mouth, and if Mr. <hi>Wheel,</hi> had knowne any ſuch here, as certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as Chriſt knew thoſe, he might have beene juſtified by the example, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe not.</p>
               <p>Therefore to conclude, ſeeing there be of thoſe who diffent from Mr. <hi>Wheel</hi> his doctrines, who have denied themſelves for the love of Chriſt as farre as be hath done, and will be ready (by Gods grace) to doe and ſuffer for the ſake of Chriſt, and the honour of Free-grace as much as himſelfe, for ſuch to be publikely defamed, and held forth as enemies to the Lord Jeſus, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:159091:32"/>like <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> and the uncircumciſed heathen, &amp;c. cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a charitable mind, nor doth it ſavour of an Apoſtolike, Goſpel-like, brotherly ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon</hi> being baniſhed and confined, till the ſeaſon of the yeere might be fit, and ſafe for her departure; ſhe thought it now needleſſe to conceale herſelfe any longer, neither would Satan loſe the opportunity of making choyce of ſo fit an inſtrument, ſo long as any hope remained to attaine his miſchievous end in darkning the ſaving truth of the Lord Jeſus, and diſturbing the peace of his Churches. Therefore ſhe began now to diſcover all her mind to ſuch as came to her, ſo that her opinions came abroad and began to take place among her old diſciples, and now ſome of them raiſed up queſtions about the immortality of the ſoule, about the reſurrection, about the morality of the Sabbath, and divers others, which the Elders finding to begin to appeare in ſome of their Churches, they took much paines (both in publike and private) to ſuppreſſe; and following the ſent from one to another, the root of all was found to be in Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon;</hi> whereupon they reſorted to her many times, labouring to convince her, but in vaine; yet they reſorted to her ſtill, to the end they might either reclaime her from her errours, or that they might beare witneſſe againſt them if occaſion were: For in a meeting of the Magiſtrates and Elders, about ſuppreſſing theſe new ſprung errours, the Elders of <hi>Boſton</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared their readineſſe to deale with Miſtris <hi>Hutchiſon</hi> in a Church way, if they had ſufficient teſtimony: for though ſhe had maintained ſome of them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times before them, yet they thought it not ſo orderly to come in as witneſſes; whereupon other of the Elders, and others collecting which they had heard from her owne mouth at ſeverall times, drew them into ſeverall heads, and ſent them to the Church of <hi>Boſton,</hi> whereupon the Church (with leave of the Magiſtrates, becauſe ſhe was a priſoner) ſent for her to appeare upon a Lecture day, being the fifteenth of the firſt moneth, and though ſhe were at her owne houſe in the Towne, yet ſhe came not into the Aſſembly till the Sermon and Prayer were ended, (pretending bodily infirmity) when ſhe was come, one of ruling Elders called her forth before the Aſſembly, (which was very great from all the parts of the Countrey) and telling her the cauſe why the Church had called her, read the ſeverall heads, which were as followeth.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That the ſoules of all men (in regard of generation) are mortall like the beaſts, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.8.</item>
                  <item>2. That in regard of Chriſts purchaſe they are immortall, ſo that Chriſt hath purchaſed the ſoules of the wicked to eternall paine, and the ſoules of the elect to eternall peace.</item>
                  <item>3. Thoſe who are united to Chriſt have in this life new bodies, and 2 bodies, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. ſhe knowes not how Jeſus Chriſt ſhould be united to this our fleſhly bodies.</item>
                  <item>4. Thoſe who have union with Chriſt, ſhall not riſe with the ſame fleſhly bodies, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.44.</item>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:159091:33"/>
                  <item>5. And that the reſurrection mentioned there, and in <hi>John</hi> 5.28. is not meant of the reſurrection of the body, but of our union here and after this life.</item>
                  <item>6. That there are no created graces in the Saints after their union with Chriſt, but before there are, for Chriſt takes them out of their hands into his owne.</item>
                  <item>7. There are no created graces in the humane nature of Chriſt, but he was onely acted by the power of the God-head.</item>
                  <item>8. The Image of God wherein <hi>Adam</hi> was made, ſhe could ſee no Scripture to warrant that it conſiſted in holineſſe, but conceived it to be in that he was made like to Chriſts manhood.</item>
                  <item>9. She had no Scripture to warrant that Chriſts manhood is now in Heaven, but the body of Chriſt is his Church.</item>
                  <item>10. We are united to Chriſt with the ſame union, that his humanity on earth was with the Deity, <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.21.</item>
                  <item>11. She conceived the Diſciples before Chriſt his death were not converted, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.3.</item>
                  <item>12. There is no evidence to be had of our good eſtate, either from abſolute or conditionall promiſes.</item>
                  <item>13. The Law is no rule of life to a Chriſtian.</item>
                  <item>14. There is no Kingdome of Heaven in Scripture but onely Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>15. There is firſt engraffing into Chriſt before union, from which a man might fall away.</item>
                  <item>16. The firſt thing God reveales to aſſure us is our election.</item>
                  <item>17. That <hi>Abraham</hi> was not in a ſaving eſtate till the 22. <hi>chap.</hi> of <hi>Gen.</hi> when hee offered <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and ſaving the firmeneſſe of Gods election, he might have periſhed notwithſtanding any work of grace that was wrought in him till then.</item>
                  <item>18. That union to Chriſt is not by faith.</item>
                  <item>19. That all commands in the word are Law, and are not a way of life, and the command of faith is a Law, and therefore killeth; ſhe ſuppoſed it to be a Law from <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27.</item>
                  <item>20. That there is no faith of Gods elect but aſſurance, there is no faith of dependance but ſuch as an hypocrite may have and fall away from, proved <hi>John</hi> 15. for by that ſhe ſaid they are in Chriſt, but Chriſt is not in them.</item>
                  <item>21. That an hypocrite may have <hi>Adams</hi> righteouſneſſe and periſh, and by that righteouſnes he is bound to the Law, but in union with Chriſt, Chriſt comes into the man, and he retaines the ſeed, and dieth, and then all manner of grace in himſelfe, but all in Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>22. There is no ſuch thing as inherent righteouſneſſe.</item>
                  <item>23. We are not bound to the Law, no not as a rule of life.</item>
                  <item>24. We are dead to all acts in ſpirituall things, and are onely acted by Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>25. Not being bound to the Law, it is not tranſgreſſion againſt the Law to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:159091:33"/>ſinne, or breake it, becauſe our ſinnes they are inward and ſpirituall, and ſo are exceeding ſinfull, and onely are againſt Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>26. Sanctification can be no evidence at all of our good eſtate.</item>
                  <item>27. That her particular revelations about future events are as infallible as any part of Scripture, and that ſhe is bound as much to beleeve them, as the Scripture, for the ſame holy Ghoſt is the author of them both.</item>
                  <item>28. That ſo farre as a man is in union with Chriſt, he can doe no duties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, and without the communion of the unregenerate part with the regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</item>
                  <item>29. That ſuch exhortations as theſe, to worke out our ſalvation with feare, to make our calling and election ſure, &amp;c. are ſpoken onely to ſuch, as are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Covenant of workes.</item>
               </list>
               <p>All which ſhe did acknowledge ſhe had ſpoken, (for a coppy of them had been ſent to her divers dayes before, and the witneſſes hands ſubſcribed, ſo as ſhe ſaw it was in vaine to deny them) then ſhe asked by what rule ſuch an Elder could come to her pretending to deſire light, and indeede to entrappe her, to which the ſame Elder anſwered that he had beene twice with her, and that he told her indeed at St. <hi>Ives,</hi> that he had beene troubled at ſome of her ſpeeches in the Court, wherein he did deſire to ſee light for the ground and meaning of them, but he profeſſed in the preſence of the Lord, that he came not to entrap her, but in compaſſion to her Soule, to helpe her out of thoſe ſnares of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, wherein he ſaw ſhe was entangled, and that before his deparure from her he did beare witneſſe againſt her opinions, and againſt her ſpirit, and did leave it ſadly upon her from the word of God: then preſently ſhe grew into paſſion againſt her Paſtor for his ſpeech againſt her at the Court after the ſentence was paſſed, which he gave a full anſwer unto, ſhewing his zeale againſt her errors, whereupon ſhe asked for what errors ſhe had beene baniſhed, profeſſing withall that ſhe held none of theſe things ſhe was now charged with, before her impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment; (ſuppoſing that whatſoever ſhould be found amiſſe, would be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to that, but it was anſwered as the truth was, that ſhe was not put to durance, but onely a favourable confinement, ſo as all of her Family and divers others, reſorted to her at their pleaſure.) But this allegation was then proved falſe, (and at her next convention more fully) for there were divers preſent, who did know ſhe ſpake untruth. Her anſwer being demanded to the firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, ſhe maintained her aſſertion that the Soules were mortall, &amp;c. alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the place in the <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> cited in the Article, and ſome other Scriptures no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the purpoſe, ſhe inſiſted much upon that in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. In the day thou eateſt, &amp;c. thou ſhalt dye, ſhe could not ſee how a Soule could be immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally miſerable, though it might be eternally miſerable, neither could ſhee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betweene the Soule and the Life; and though ſhe were preſſed by many Scriptures and reaſons alleadged by the Elders of the ſame, and other Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, ſo as ſhe could not give any anſwer to them, yet ſhe ſtood to her opinion, till at length a ſtranger being deſired to ſpeake to the point, and hee opening to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:159091:34"/>her the difference betweene the Soule and the Life, the firſt being a ſpirituall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and the other the union of that with the body; ſhe then confeſſed ſhe ſaw more light then before, and ſo with ſome difficulty was brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe her error in that point. Wherein was to be obſerved that though he ſpake to very good purpoſe, and ſo clearely convinced her as ſhe could not gain-ſay, yet it was evident ſhee was convinced before, but ſhe could not give the honour of it to her owne Paſtor or teacher, nor to any of the other Elders, whom ſhe ſlighted had ſo much.</p>
               <p>Then they proceeded to the third, fourth, and fifth Articles, about the body and the refurrection of the old, which ſhee maintained according to the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and though ſhee were not able to give any reaſonable anſwer to the many places of the Scripture, and other arguments which were brought to convince her, yet ſhee ſtill perſiſted in her errour, giving froward ſpeeches to ſome that ſpake to her, as when one of the Elders uſed this argument, that if the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection were only our union with Chriſt, then all that are united, are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the reſurrection, and therefore are neither to marry, nor to give in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and ſo by conſequence, there ought to bee community of women; ſhee told him that hee ſpake like the Phariſees, who ſaid that Chriſt had a devill, becauſe that <hi>Abraham</hi> were dead and the Prophets, and yet hee had ſaid, that thoſe which eate his fleſh, ſhould never dye, not taking the ſpeech in the true meaning, ſo did hee (ſaid ſhee) who brought that argument, for it is ſaid there, they ſhould bee like the Angels, &amp;c. The Elders of <hi>Boſton</hi> finding her thus ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, propounded to the Church for an admonition to bee given her, to which all the Church conſented, except two of her ſons, who becauſe they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted to defend her, were under admonition alſo. Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> gave the admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and firſt to her ſons, laying it ſadly upon them, that they would give ſuch way to their naturall affection, as for preſerving her honour, they ſhould make a breach upon the honour of Chriſt, and upon their Covenant with the Church, and withall teare the very bowels of their ſoule, by hardning her in her ſin: In this admonition to her, firſt, hee remembred her of the good way ſhee was in at her firſt comming, in helping to diſcover to divers, the falſe bottom they ſtood upon, in truſting to legall works without Chriſt; then hee ſhewed her, how by falling into theſe groſſe and fundamentall errors, ſhee had loſt the honour of her former ſervice, and done more wrong to Chriſt and his Church, then formerly ſhee had done good, and ſo laid her ſin to her conſcience with much zeale and ſolemnity, hee admoniſhed her alſo of the height of ſpirit, then hee ſpake to the ſiders of the Church, and adviſed them to take heed of her opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to with-hold all countenance and reſpects from her, leſt they ſhould harden her in her ſin: ſo ſhee was diſmiſſed and appointed to appeare againe that day ſevennight.</p>
               <p>The Count had ordered that ſhee ſhould return to <hi>Roxbury</hi> again, but upon intimation that her ſpirit began to fall, ſhee was permitted to remain at Mr. <hi>Cottons</hi> houſe (where <hi>Davenport</hi> was alſo kept) who before her next appearing,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:159091:34"/>did both take much pains with her, and prevailed ſo far, that ſhee did acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge her errour in all the Articles (except the laſt) and accordingly ſhee wrote down her anſwers to them all, when the day came, and ſhee was called forth and the Articles read again to her, ſhee delivered in her anſwers in writing, which were alſo read, and being then willing to ſpeak to the Congregation for their further ſatisfaction, ſhee did acknowledge that ſhee had greatly erred, and that God had left her to her ſelf herein, becauſe ſhee had ſo much under-natured his Ordinances, both in ſlighting the Magiſtrates at the Court, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Elders of the Church, and confeſſed that when ſhee was at the Court, ſhee looked only at ſuch failings as ſhee apprehended in the Magiſtrates procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, without having regard to the place they were in and that the ſpeeches ſhee then uſed about her revelations were raſh, and without ground, and ſhee deſired the prayers of the Church for her.</p>
               <p>Thus farre ſhee went on well, and the Aſſembly conceived hope of her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, but in her anſwers to the ſeverall articles, ſhee gave no ſatisfaction, becauſe in diverſe of them ſhee anſwered by circumlocutions, and ſeemed to lay all the faults in her expreſſions, which occaſioned ſome of the Elders to deſire ſhee might expreſſe her ſelf more cleerly, and for that ever ſhee was demanded about the Article, whether ſhee were not, or had not been of that judgement, that there is no inherent righteouſneſſe in the Saints, but thoſe gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which are aſcribed to them that are only in Chriſt as the ſubject? to which ſhee anſwered, that ſhee was never of that judgement, howſoever by her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions ſhee might ſeem to bee ſo; and this ſhee affirmed with ſuch confidence as bred great aſtoniſhment in many, who had known the contrary, and diverſe alledged her own ſayings and reaſonings, both before her confinement and ſince, which did manifeſt to all that were preſent, that ſhee knew that ſhee ſpake untruth, for it was proved that ſhee had alledged that in <hi>Eſay</hi> 53. By his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhall my righteous ſervant juſtifie many; which ſhee had maintained to bee meant of a knowledge in Chriſt, and not in us; ſo likewiſe that in <hi>Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> I live by the faith of the Son of God, which ſhee ſaid was the faith of Chriſt, and not any faith inherent in us; alſo, that ſhee had maintained, that Chriſt is our ſanctification in the ſame ſort that hee is our juſtification, and that ſhee had ſaid, that ſhee would not pray for grace, but for Chriſt, and that (when ſhe had been preſſed with diverſe Scriptures, which ſpake of waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and creating a new heart, and writing the Law in the heart, &amp;c.) ſhee had denyed; that they did mean any ſanctification in us: There were diverſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men alſo with whom ſhee had dealt about the ſame point, who (if their mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty had not reſtrained them) would have born witneſſe againſt her herein, (as themſelves after confeſſed) wherefore the Elders preſſed her very earneſtly to remember her ſelf, and not to ſtand ſo obſtinately to maintain ſo manifeſt an untruth, but ſhee was deafe of that eare, and would not acknowledge that ſhee had been at any time of that judgement, howſoever her expreſſions were; Then Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> told the Aſſembly, that whereas ſhee had been formerly dealt with
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:159091:35"/>for matter of doctrine, he had (according to the duty of his place being the teacher of that Church) proceeded againſt unto admonition, but now the caſe being altered, and ſhe being in queſtion for maintaining of untruth, which is matter of manners, he muſt leave the buſineſſe to the Paſtor, Mr. <hi>Wilſon</hi> to goe on with her, but withall declared his judgement in the caſe from that in <hi>Revel.</hi> 22. that ſuch as make and maintaine a lye, ought to be caſt out of the Church; and whereas two or three pleaded that ſhe might firſt have a ſecond admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to that in <hi>Titus</hi> 3.10. he anſwered that that was onely for ſuch as erred in point of doctrine, but ſuch as ſhall notoriouſly offend in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of converſation, ought to be preſently caſt out, as he proved by <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> and the inceſtuous Corinthian; (and as appeares by that of <hi>Simin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi>) and for her owne part though ſhe heard this moved in her behalfe, that ſhe might have a further reſpite, yet ſhe her ſelfe never deſired it: ſo the Paſtor went on, and propounding it to the Church, to know whether they were all agreed, that ſhe ſhould be caſt out, and a full conſent appearing (after the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all manner) by their ſilence, after a convenient pauſe he proceeded, and denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the ſentence of excommunication againſt her, and ſhe was commanded to depart out of the Aſſembly. In her going forth, one ſtanding at the dore, ſaid, The Lord ſanctifie this unto you, to whom ſhe made anſwer, The Lord judgeth not as man judgeth, better to be caſt out of the Church then to deny Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thus it hath pleaſed the Lord to have compaſſion of his poore Churches here, and to diſcover this great impoſter, an inſtrument of Satan ſo fitted and trained to his ſervice for interrupting the paſſage, Kingdome in this part of the world, and poyſoning the Churches here planted, as no ſtory records the like of a woman, ſince that mentioned in the <hi>Revelation;</hi> it would make a large vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume to lay downe all paſſages, I will onely obſerve ſome few, which were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to all that knew her courſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In her entrance I obſerve,
<list>
                     <item>1. Her entrance.</item>
                     <item>2. Her progreſſe.</item>
                     <item>3. Her down fall.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The foundation ſhe laid was (or rather ſeemed to be) Chriſt and Free-Grace.</item>
                  <item>2. Rule ſhe pretended to walke by, was onely the Scripture.</item>
                  <item>3. The light to diſcerne this rule, was onely the holy Ghoſt.</item>
                  <item>4. The perſons ſhe converſed with were (for the moſt part) Chriſtians in Church Covenant.</item>
                  <item>5. Her ordinary talke was about the things of the Kingdome of God.</item>
                  <item>6. Her uſuall converſation was in the way of righteouſneſſe and kindneſſe.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Thus ſhe entred and made up the firſt act of her courſe.</p>
               <p>In her progeſſe I obſerve,</p>
               <p>Firſt, her ſucceſſe, ſhe had in a ſhort time inſinuated her ſelfe into the hearts of much of the people (yea of many of the moſt wiſe and godly) who grew
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:159091:35"/>into ſo reverent an eſteeme of her godlineſſe, and ſpirituall gifts, as they look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at her as a Propheteſſe, raiſed up of God for ſome great worke now at hand, as the calling of the Jewes, &amp;c. ſo as ſhe had more reſort to her for counſell about matter of conſcience, and clearing up mens ſpirituall eſtates, then any Miniſter (I might ſay all the Elders) in the Country.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Pride and arraigning of her ſpirit.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. In framing a new way of converſation and evidencing thereof, carried along in the diſtinction betweene the Covenant of workes, which ſhe would have no otherwiſe differenced, but by an immediate Revelation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</item>
                  <item>2. In deſpiſing all (both Elders and Chriſtians) who went not her way, and laying them under a Covenant of workes.</item>
                  <item>3. In taking upon her infallibly to know theelection of others, ſo as ſhe would ſay, that if ſhe had but one halfe houres talke with a man, ſhe would tell whether he were elect or not.</item>
                  <item>4. Her impatience of oppoſition, which appeares in diver paſſages before.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Thirdly, Her skill and cunning to deviſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. In that ſhe ſtill pretended ſhe was of Mr. <hi>Cottons</hi> judgement in all things.</item>
                  <item>2. In covering her errors by doubtfull expreſſions.</item>
                  <item>3. In ſhadowing the true end, and abuſe of her weekely meetings under the name of repeating Mr. <hi>Cottons</hi> Sormons.</item>
                  <item>4. In her method of practiſe to bring the conſcience under a falſe terror, by working that an argument of a Covenant of workes, which no Chriſtian can have comfort without, viz. of ſanctification, or qualifications, (as ſhe termed it.)</item>
                  <item>5. In her conſident profeſſion of her owne good eſtate, and the clearneſſe and comfort of it, obtained in the ſame way of waiting for immediate Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which ſhe held out to others.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In her downefall there may be obſerved the Lords faithfulneſſe in honouring and juſtifying his owne Ordinances.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In that hee made her to cleare the juſtice of the Court, by confeſſing the vanity of her revelations, &amp;c. and her ſinne in deſpiſing his Miniſters.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In that the judgement and ſentence of the Church hath concurred with that of the Court in her rejection, ſo that ſhe is caſt out of both as an unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy member of either.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Juſtice of God in giving her up to thoſe deluſions, and to that impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency in venting and maintaining them, as ſhould bring her under that cenſure, which (not long before) ſhe had endeavoured and expected to have brought upon ſome other, who oppoſed her proceedings.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That ſhe who was in ſuch eſteeme in the Church for ſoundneſſe of Judgement and ſincerity of heart (but a few moneths before) ſhould now come under ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition for many foule and fundamentall errors, and after be caſt out for notorious lying.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:159091:36"/>5. That ſhee who was wont to bee ſo conſident of her ſpirituall good eſtate, and ready (undeſired) to hold it forth to others (being preſſed now at her laſt appearance before the Church to give ſome proofe of it) ſhould bee wholly ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in that matter.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whereas upon the ſentence of the Court againſt her, ſhee boaſted highly of her ſufferings for Chriſt, &amp;c. it was noted by one of the Elders (who bare witneſſe againſt her errors) that the ſpirit of glory promiſed in <hi>Pet.</hi> to thoſe who ſuffer for well-doing, did not come upon her, but a ſpirit of deluſion, and damnable error, which as it had poſſeſſed her before, ſo it became more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall and evident by her ſufferings.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Here is to bee ſeen the preſence of God in his Ordinances, when they are faithfully attended according to his holy will, although not free from human infirmities: This <hi>American Jeſabel</hi> kept her ſtrength and reputation, even among the people of God, till the hand of Civill Juſtice laid hold on her, and then ſhee began evidently to decline, and the faithfull to bee freed from her forgeries; and now in this laſt act, when ſhee might have expected (as moſt likely ſhee did) by her ſeeming repentance of her errors, and confeſſing her under valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Ordinances of Magiſtracy and Miniſtracy, to have redeemed her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in point of ſincerity, and yet have made good all her former work, and kept open a back doore to have returned to her vomit again, by her para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſticall retractions, and denying any change in her judgement, yet ſuch was the preſence and bleſſing of God in his own Ordinance, that this ſubtilty of Satan was diſcovered to her utter ſhame and confuſion, and to the ſetting at liberty of many godly hearts, that had been captivated by her to that day; and that Church which by her means was brought under much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy, and neere to diſſolution, was hereby ſweetly repaired, and a hopefull way of eſtabliſhment, and her diſſembled repentance clterly detected, God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving her up ſince the ſentence of excommunication, to that hardneſſe of heart, as ſhee is not affected with any remorſe but glories in it, and feares not the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God, which ſhe lyes under, as if God did work contrary to his own word, and looſed from heaven, while his Church had bound upon earth.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
